大家好 我是Destin
Hey, it's me, Destin.
欢迎观看天天大聪明
Welcome back to Smarter Every Day, 2.
很高兴遇到大家
Glad to have you.
今天我们将对Luke Talley进行一次超长采访
So today we are going to do the long interview with Luke Talley.
主频道上有一个剪辑版 短一点 这个视频是完整版
There's a shorter version
over on the main channel, but this is like the whole shebang.
今天采访的这位Luke Talley是六十年代IBM的一位工程师
Today we are going to talk to Luke Talley, who is an IBM engineer in the sixties,
他曾参与研发土星五号火箭顶端的仪器舱
and he worked on the instrument unit right up near
the top of the Saturn five rocket.
这个部分控制土星五号所有的分级 比如一级关机 二级点火等
And it controlled all the different stages of the Saturn five, things
like main engine cutoff, for example, and then that would launch the second stage.
这个仪器舱会控制所有这些东西
So this instrument unit controlled all of that stuff.
因为请他来介绍土星五号的各部分再合适不过了
And so he's an ideal person to talk to about how the Saturn five work.
不仅如此 他还是个得过奖的工程师
But not only that, he is an award winning engineer,
在60年代 他们整了个"载人航天意识流企划"
for example, back in the sixties they had this thing called the manned spaceflight Awareness program.
简单来讲就是告诉他们 "你们的工作非常重要"
And the whole idea was to tell employees like, Hey, your job matters
因为宇航员的命都在你们手里
because the safety of the astronauts is in your hands.
而Luke和他的同事 这位叫Nate 发现有这样一条同轴缆
For example, Luke and his coworker Nate here, there was a coaxial cable
可能会在太阳照射下熔化 而他们发现了这个设计漏洞
that would melt when it got hit by the sun, and they figured this out.
他们进行了测试 并修复这点
They ran a test and they fixed it.
作为奖励 Luke赢得了"载人航天意识流奖"
And as a result of that, Luke won a manned spaceflight awareness award.
其中一部分奖励就是可以去肯尼迪航天中心现场观看阿波罗13号的发射
And part of that award was he got a trip to go to Kennedy
to watch the Apollo 13 launch, which is so cool.
然后是这个
Here's this.
这就是奖状了
This was kind of the whole deal here.
奖状右下角这里 有Alan Shepard的签名
第一位进入太空的美国人 阿波罗14号指令长
You can see on this award, it's signed by Alan Shepard.
写着"Luke 我们的命就交给你啦"
It said, Luke, we stake our lives on employee awareness.
"Alan Shepard 敬上" 牛逼吧
Alan Shepard How cool is that?
专门给Luke的签名
A personal autograph specifically to Luke?
真的太牛逼了
That's really, really cool.
之后他们两口子来了这里
They went down there.
这是Luke和Kitty在观看阿波罗13号的发射 太酷炫了
This is Luke and Kitty at the Apollo 13
launch, which is so very, very cool.
真的很激动能跟大家分享这个
I'm excited to show this to you.
如果你喜欢这个视频 请到下面的链接赞助
If you enjoy this video, please
consider supporting on patreon.com/smartereveryday
不去也没事
If not, no big deal.
我很期待能听些关于土星五号的第一手消息
I'm just excited to learn more about the Saturn five rocket straight
from the horse's mouth.
我们一起跟随Luke Talley 一起天天大聪明吧~
Let's go get smarter every day with Luke Talley.
您想怎么讲 从火箭尖开始还是从下面开始?
How do you want to do it? Tip tail or tail tip.
我们从尾巴开始吧 一路往火箭尖走
We'll start the tail and walk our way up.
行
Okay.
我们接下来要听亲历者关于土星五号的第一手的讲解
We're going to learn all about the Saturn five from the horse's mouth.
那我们先往尾巴走吧 到了再开始
So we'll head down there and we'll get started.
-一共三级的火箭是吧  -嗯
So three stages, right? Yep.
三级
Three stages.
一套仪器舱
An instrument unit.
这里面您最喜欢哪一部分?
Which. What's your most favorite what's your favorite part of the whole thing?
我倒无所谓什么"最喜欢" 但我觉得最……
I don't know about the favorite, but the most
最震撼的是一会儿到一级那边能看到的发动机
phenomenal is the engines that we'll look at on the first day.
光是看到发动机的体积 想想它们怎么工作的就头皮发麻
Really just the sheer size and magnitude of
how those things operate is mind boggling.
今天的计算机系统已经非常非常小了
That's the computer system in today's
world was very
今天的计算机系统已经非常非常小了
small.
现在的16000字的存储
16,000 words of memory in today.
我们当时用的计算机上面的晶体管
The transistors we used on our computer,
没有集成电路 没有微处理器
we didn't have integrated circuits or microprocessors.
土星五号计算机上用的晶体管要32分之一平方英寸
The transistors that we're used to in
约20mm²
土星五号计算机上用的晶体管要32分之一平方英寸
the Saturn computer were about 32nd of an inch square.
一共要用87000个晶体管
We had about 87,000 transistors
在今天 上太空的设备里 之前那样晶体管的面积中
In the size in the space of one of those transistors,
IBM的设备可以放进180万个晶体管
today, IBM equipment that's in the field has 18 million transistors.
好大的差距呀
Quite a big difference there.
是吧 世界有一点点变化~
So things have changed a little bit.
说真的 咱们真的很佩服那些
Let's say all you've got to you've got
参与项目的人 设计这些东西的人
to admire the people that program, that thing and designed
他们创造了这样庞大复杂的机器
the intricate mechanism of how that thing worked
让这样的庞然大物上天 但是一次都——
to fly this giant rocket we never had a single
土星系列火箭是我知道的唯一一款
Saturn is the only rocket that I know of
没有发生过严重事故的火箭
that never had a catastrophic failure.
确实有过这样那样的地方工作异常
We had things that didn't work once in a while here and there.
而且阿波罗一号飞船还有过亡人事故
And, you know, we had a victim on the next flight.
但总体来说 土星系列火箭仍然是非常成功的
All in all, this was a really successful project.
太牛了
That's amazing.
-参与这样的项目感觉怎么样?  -老爽了
What was it like to be a part of something like this It is great.
您想从哪里开始讲?
Where you start.
我猜咱们肯定会讲喷管的吧?
I guess we got to see the bell, don't we?
-就从这开始吧  -好
Just start back here  All right
我管这个叫
Well, I call this the.
这个土星五号展厅里一进来就让人惊掉下巴的地方
This is the mouth dropping entrance of the Saturn hall
12.2英尺 3.7米
你一进展厅就能看到这五台直径大约12英尺的发动机
You come in here and you see these Each of these about 12 feet in diameter.
690吨
每台都能提供150万磅的推力
Each of these engines now produce one and a half million pounds of thrust each.
外围四个发动机可以摆动
The four outer engines are gimble.
说白了可以动
That is, they can move.
任意方向 5度的摆动
They can move anywhere within a one and anywhere within a five degree circle
在飞行中由三级顶部的仪器舱控制
controlled by the computer up in the instrument unit,
which is on top of the third stage during the flight.
一级大约会在一分钟的时候达到音速
The first stage will go through the speed of sound at about 60 seconds.
随后就是火箭的最大动压点
Shortly after that, you get the maximum aerodynamic pressure on this vehicle
就像两只大手抓着火箭疯狂蹂躏一样
and it is like two giant hands have it shaking it for all it's worth.
麻烦您能转过身看这里吗?
Look at your eye here. Can you turn around?
好的好的
There we go.
好 您继续
Yeah go for it.
外圈每台发动机可以在5度范围内摆动
Each of the engines can move anywhere in a five degree circle
当火箭达到音速后 就会来到最大动压点
as we go through the speed of sound and we get maximum aerodynamic pressure,
发动机大约会摆动1.5度左右
we would see them move about one and a half degrees.
绝大多数时间我们能看到的最大摆动就是这样了
That's the most we ever saw move most of the time,
这两句存疑
除了在一些振动的时候
except in that half vibration period.
可能摆动会小到半度
They would move at maybe a half a degree.
-而它们以此控制火箭的指向?  -是的
And that was actually pointing the rocket. Yes.
它们控制火箭往哪飞
And that steers the rocket.
调整外围四台发动机的朝向 控制火箭的飞行
So you move these four out of the engines as you need to to steer the rocket.
摆在展厅里的这个火箭 从头到尾
Now, the rocket that's in here, the structure that's here
经常会有人问 它上过天吗?
is we get the question, did it fly?
肯定没上过
Well, no, it didn't fly.
飞了就捡不回来了
If it flies, we don't get it back.
这里展出的是在马歇尔太空飞行中心进行结构测试的部件
So the structure in here was actually the structural test model
for the testing at Marshall Space Flight Center
就是把火箭竖起来
Sort of stood this thing up in it.
然后给它施加力 看看它的震动情况
But forces like expected to see vibrated. It just generally beat it up.
因为这些发动机推举火箭升空的时候
Well, when this thing is flying in these engines,
计算机会给发动机下达指令进行摆动
the computer sending the commands down to steer the rocket by moving the engine,
当发动机进行摆动的时候 不但会让火箭转弯 还会让它自己变形
When you move the engine, you not only move the rocket, but you cause it to flex.
这些发动机推力太大了 在飞行中的一些时刻
These engines are so powerful that there are points in the flight
如果发动机摆动得太快 别说发动机 连火箭自己都会被生生掰断
where if you move this engine too
quick, you break it in two, break the rocket into, not the engine.
所以当时会进行很多测试
So the measures that were made were
比如所谓"弯曲模态"和"结构动力模态"
what they call bending modes and structural dynamic modes.
用这些数据来为计算机编程
That information was used to program our computer so that we knew at points
告诉计算机飞行的哪些时刻可以怎样摆动发动机
and what points in the flight can we move the engine more or less
based on the data that came out of these tests.
这是我们进行过的一系列测试之一
So that was one series of tests that were run.
按我的理解
So if I understand.
呃 我们现在在火箭的底部
Okay, so so we're at the back end of the rocket.
这些发动机型号是什么来着?
And what are these engines what are they called?
F-1
These are called F-1.
我不知道为什么叫这个名字
I have no idea why the F-1.
只是个代号罢了
That's just the number.
这些F-1发动机
Okay. They're called F-1 engines.
690吨
每台可以提供150万磅的推力
Each is producing one and a half million pounds of thrust.
于我而言 这些发动机最震撼的是它们
The thing that to me is just incredible is each one of these engines.
使用的燃料煤油 氧化剂是液氧
Now, the fuel is kerosene and liquid oxygen, of course, oxidizer.
每台发动机 每秒会消耗一吨的煤油和两吨的液氧 每台!
This thing burns a ton of kerosene
and two tons of liquid oxygen every second, each engine.
哇 平常要说"成吨的"都是夸张的说法
That's because when you say, man, this this does a ton of whatever,
that's what you kind of you're doing hyperbole,
但这里真的是字面意义的"每秒一吨"的煤油
but you're literally saying a ton of kerosene.
而且是每台 所以加起来五台发动机每秒就是15吨的燃料
Per engine. So these these five engines are burning 15 tons of propellant every second.
所以火箭的质量变化会非常快
So the mass of this thing changes very rapidly
从而影响火箭的弯曲模态
and that affects these blending modes.
所以我们要对这些进行测试 然后编写程序
So we had to measure that kind of stuff and program again
让计算机知道不能……
to the computer system so that we knew not to.
所以您刚刚提到这些发动机是可以摆动的
So you're saying each of these each of these engines can move.
外围四个可以摆动 中央是固定的
Each of the four out or engines can move the center engine fixed, it doesn't move.
呃 是怎么摆动的?
Well. How do they move it?
有作动器
They have they have actuators.
-您能指出在哪吗?  -这里
-Will you show me?   -These things.
能看到红点吗?
Can you see this pointer?
嗯 勉强能看到
Yeah, a little bit.
这就是火箭的摆动作动器
This engine has an actuator.
这里有一个 靠外侧还有一个
There's an actuator here and then there's another one up on the other side of it up there.
每台发动机两个作动器
So two actuators per engine.
作动器是液压的 伺服控制 由仪器舱电脑下达指令
The actuator is a hydraulic actuator servo mechanism under control of the computer in the instrument unit.
使用煤油作为液压油
and they're using the kerosene as their hydraulic fluid.
燃料箱里就有足够压力 所以不需要泵了
There's plenty of pressure in the tank, so I don't need a pump,
这样可以节省很多重量和复杂度
so I'm saving weight and complexity and so forth.
看着这样的庞然大物 你问我复杂度节省什么的有在做吗?
And they look at it and you say, Are you sure we saved any complexity?
的确有
But that's true.
哦! 火箭上有那么多飞行设备需要液压油
Oh, so there's like a lot of aerodynamic or aerospace systems have a hydraulic fluid.
当然 各种地方都需要 上面级也有它自己的液压油
You have a hydraulic fluid. Well, the upper stages have to have the hydraulic fluid.
而这里我们用的是煤油
But this thing we just use the kerosene.
有趣
Interesting.
这样能省下一大堆管路
And in that saves a whole set of piping.
没错 减少复杂度 提高可靠性
Oh, more set of piping complexity affects your reliability.
这个东西最最重要的就是 可靠性
Number one concern is reliability in this thing.
你需要让每个部件尽可能完美 毕竟它……
You ought to have it as perfect as you can because there's,
加起来可能有五百万个零件
you know, there's 5 million parts or something like that in this thing.
所以如果每个部件可靠性只有0.9 那五百万次方就没法看了
So every part, if it's point nine times, I got 5 million of them and that ain't real good.
所以我需要可靠性是零点九九九九……
So I need point nine.
我需要可靠性99.999% 才能达到任务需求 让整个火箭飞上天
And you know, so I got to have 99.999 something
percent chance of making the mission in order for all this stuff to work. That has to.
这是其中一个重要的点
So that's one of the main issues.
现在说发动机 你能看到我指的地方吗?
Now the the engine itself, as you look at the engine, can you look up there?
红点不太清楚 但我知道您指的是这个区域
I can barely see your laser, but you're pointing in this area right here.
上面是燃烧室 后面是喷管和延伸段
So we have the thrust chamber and then we have a nozzle extension on the back.
但这台发动机有趣的地方在画面上方这个圆柱的地方
But the interesting part of this engine is all this is a magnet up above the thrust chamber.
这是一个驱动泵的涡轮发动机
Okay? This is a jet engine to drive the pumps
它保证了发动机每秒三吨燃料的供给
to get three tons of propellant through that engine every second.
这里就有涡轮
So this is a jet turbine in here.
轴功率 55000马力 约41兆瓦
而这个涡轮的功率 大概是五万多马力
And this jet turbine is about a 50 some odd thousand horsepower turbine.
亨茨维尔外面的直升机 功率大约是5000-7000马力
The helicopters that fly around Huntsville, probably 5 to 7000 horsepower engines.
所以这个涡轮真的很恐怖
So this is a monster turbine.
更有意思的 可能是 发动机的推力室
The probably one of the more interesting points of it is the thrust chamber itself.
3300摄氏度
它的喉部温度大约是5900华氏度
The throat temperature is 5900 degrees.
几乎能熔化一切东西了
That melt stuff. That will melt any of these materials.
而解决办法 如果你仔细看的话
So what they do is, if you can see this,
这部分有很多纤细的管路从发动机喉部延伸下来
it has fine tubes running down this thrust chamber region here.
煤油在参与燃烧前 会流经这些管路 再经其他管路向上流回发动机
The kerosene before it's burned is actually routed down
these tubes, comes down through the tubes, goes back up another set of tubes.
然后进入发动机燃烧
Then in the engine to burn it.
靠内壁中燃料的流动来冷却发动机 防止自己被熔化
And the flow of that in the wall is how you're cooling that engine to keep it from melt.
我记得氧化剂是液氧对吧?
Now, the oxygen was was liquid oxygen, right?
那煤油会用过冷的煤油吗? 还是
Was the kerosene super cold or.
不 只是普通的液体煤油
No, it's just plain old liquid kerosene.
现在不少火箭开始使用甲烷做燃料了
Now, a lot of the engine, a lot of the rockets today
as basic somebody like that, they're using methane.
甲烷 煤油这些都是碳氢化合物嘛
Well, methane, kerosene, still hydrocarbons and so forth.
而甲烷是比较能压缩的
Methane is compressible.
所以运输起来比较方便
So it's a lot easier to transport and move around
煤油是液态的 没法压缩 所以本身就比较重
kerosene liquids, not compressible. So a little bit heavier to to deal with.
燃料是怎么加压的?
How do you do that?
是把液面上方的气体加压吗? 还是容积式的那种泵?
Do you put like air over the liquid and pressurize the air or you pump it by positive displacement?
这些燃料箱呢
These these tanks, the
氧箱是靠把热的氧气泵回储箱顶部来加压的
oxygen tank, of course, it's pressurized with pumping
heated oxygen back into top of the tank, create pressure.
但在燃料箱里 我们用的是氦
But now in the fuel tank, we actually use helium to take helium.
实际上在涡轮的出口这里
And in fact, on the output of the turbine up there,
涡轮废气这有几组换热器
there are a couple of heat exchangers in the turbine exhaust.
它本质是一个驱动泵的涡轮发动机 所以这里相当于是发动机的排气口
It's a it's a jet turbine driving the pumps, which is like in a jet engine exhaust.
所以废气这里会有几组换热器
So that exhaust has a couple of heat exchangers in there.
一部分液氧会从氧箱带过来
One of them, you bring oxygen down from the tank,
流经这里的换热器 加热 增压
run it through the heat exchanger, heated up, raises the pressure,
再泵回顶部的储箱 从而实现增压
put that pressurized back in the top of the tank, gives you the pressure.
而氧箱里还有氦气瓶
We carry helium bottles inside the liquid oxygen tank.
我们会让氦流经另一个换热器
So we're bringing the helium down through another heat exchanger,
加热增压后送入燃料箱的顶部
heated up and put it back into the top of the kerosene tank.
可不能把氧气怼进燃料箱里
You don't put oxygen in the fuel tank.
不然就成大号烟花了
Oh, yeah. Okay. And because it blow up.
所以燃料箱使用的是氦气增压
So it's a pressure and use helium as a pressure.
选择氦气是因为它是惰性气体
And the reason it's helium is because it's an inert gas.
-这样两者不反应 有趣  -嗯
Right. Okay. And it won't react. Yeah. Interesting.
-那么 燃料和氧化剂都被泵到主燃烧室里?  -对
And so you, you throw all that down in here into the combustion chamber? Yep.
那里长什么样? 那个用来混合两者的喷注盘
And what does that look like? That it's just a mixture plate that the.
喷注盘就是一个特别大的 有大约6000个孔的圆盘
The injector plate is just a large diameter plate has about 6000 holes in it.
有的孔喷煤油 有的孔喷液氧
Some of the holes are squirt kerosene, some of the holes are squirting liquid oxygen.
这个馆内有展示吗?
Do we have something here in the museum?
-有的  -好 那我们一会看看吧
They says. Yeah, so we can see that. Interesting.
您刚刚说外围的四台发动机是可摆动的对吧
And so you said the four on the outside would gimbal it, Right?
而中央的发动机并不摆动
But the one in the middle does not.
那您的计算机是如何知道该控制哪一个的?
So how do you with the computer, how would you know which ones to control.
在仪器舱里有一个制导平台 可以告诉火箭自己在哪里
Well your guidance your you have a guidance platform in the instrument unit and this tell you where you are
同时还存储了发射数据 告诉火箭自己应该在哪
and you have a stored profile of where you ought to be.
然后火箭会每秒25次读取制导平台的数值进行计算
So 25 times a second, he's reading the guidance platform and calculating or part of the calculation.
对比火箭现在在哪 与火箭应该在哪
About where where am I versus where should I be.
基于计算结果 仪器舱发出指令 让哪台发动机怎么动 让火箭往哪飞
And so based on that, he determines which engines
need to be gimbled in order to steer you in the right direction.
什么时候俯仰 偏航 滚转
Do I need pitch? Do I need yaw? Do I need roll? Do I need all the above?
就是这样运行的
And all of that's done in the.
-而这是一套闭环系统  -是的
And it's a closed loop system. Yeah.
有意思 真厉害
That's amazing. Okay. That's incredible.
中央的那台发动机 我发现周围有几个固定结构
So that one right in the middle, I'm noticing that you've got these. These rigid structures there.
-它们是连到哪的? 这个绿色的大平板也会跟着上天吗?  -是的
What does that going into, this plate that we're seeing? Was that on the actual flight hardware. Yeah.
底下这些所有东西 发动机 都会包一层保温层
Now all of this on the base, the engines and the base were all covered with an insulating blanket.
inconel
上面的主燃烧室 全都是由铬镍铁合金制成的
The thrust chamber up there ... that's all made out of a metal called inconel,
镍 钴 铬之类 非常耐腐蚀
nickel, cobalt, chromium, very corrosion resistant.
这玩意一秒消耗整整两吨的液氧
This sucker burning two tons of oxygen every second.
用普通钢铁(做燃烧室)的话 早就熔化了
So if it's a piece of iron, it would melt.
一瞬间就烧没了
It would rust in a heartbeat.
因此它们会有薄薄的一层铬镍铁合金层
So they had inconel blankets, layer of thin inconel,
然后可能会有一层石棉 然后再来一层
and then probably probably asbestos and then another layer.
整个发动机都会给包起来
And it was all the engines. They had just blankets on the engine.
这部分的详细内容可以查看
av204353929
底部每台发动机都包起来
They had blankets on the base.
因为当我们稍微飞出大气的时候
The problem we have with this thing, once you get a little out of the atmosphere,
中央发动机会吸入周围发动机废气的热量
that center engine gets extremely hot from all the heat coming off of these.
所以我们要尽量保证中央发动机不会过热
So you're trying to keep as much heat as you can away from that center.
啊 有意思 因为飞行的时候中央的部分会形成低压区
And oh, interesting, because you're kind of in a low pressure zone back here.
没错没错
Oh, yeah. Yeah.
因为火箭在向前飞 所以正后方这里会把气流吸回来
Because you're moving forward and you got this little pocket.
-对  -有趣
Right. Interesting.
那中央发动机的热量管理 和其它的不同吗?
So the thermal management on the center engine, was it different than the outside?
不 所有发动机都一样的
No, the engines are the same.
我们只是单纯用隔热毯给它们包起来
So we just everything is blanketed with an insulating blanket
别让其他四台发动机的热量倾泻到中央发动机上
to try to keep all the heat in the engines instead of dumping it over at four to center engine.
有意思
Interesting.
我第一次知道这个 有意思
I didn't know that. That's amazing.
我们这有句话是这样说的 ↓
"hotter than a two-dollar pistol" 俚语 形容很热/很生气
George Jones一首歌有提到
We say in south Alabama, it's hotter than a two-dollar pistol.
哈哈哈 我也喜欢那首歌
Yeah. I like that song, too.
太逗了
That's amazing.
在这你还能看到一些部件是黄色的
So in here, as you look at this thing, you see there are parts on here that are yellow.
所有黄色的部件都是地面支撑设备
Anything in here that's yellow is ground handling equipment.
你看到那些黄色的托盘了吗
So you see those those plates are there.
这样火箭才能沿着那个方向躺下去
And that's so this thing will sag as it's laying on its side.
当火箭竖起在发射台的时候
So once you get it up, stand on the pad.
就要把黄色的部分移走
You would remove the yellow pieces.
我们再往前走还能看见很多这样的东西
We'll see a lot more of that on the forward section.
它们是原本设计中就有的硬件吗?
And that's the original design for the hardware.
-是的  -好的 跟您走
Okay. All right. Following you.
这就是一级火箭了 它要工作多久?
So that's the first stage. How long would the first stage fire?
64km       2.2km/s
一级会燃烧两分半钟 把火箭送到40英里高空 时速5000英里
Okay, so the first stage burn, two and a half minutes takes them up to about 40 miles and 5000 miles an hour.
那个高度
Now, at that altitude,
64km
呃 其实挺高的 40英里呢
you're you're pretty high, you know, 40 miles up.
在一二级分离的时候 一级会继续往上飞
Well, he's still climbing as his separation.
在分离的时候 你想想 后面每个发动机就要9吨
So when things separate, you think each of these engines back here is 9 tons.
加一起就是45吨的发动机 接在一个超大的铝罐上
So we've got 45 tons of engines they attached to a craft member of aluminum.
铝罐又是20吨
That's another about 20 tons.
加起来就是个六七十吨的东西
So we've got 60, 70 tons of stuff.
可能你会觉得火箭还会继续飞
So you would think the rocket is climbing.
而下面级会这样直接掉下来
He would do this and fall.
2.2km/s
但当时它的速度有每小时5000英里
But he's going 5000 miles an hour.
当它和二级分离的时候 它的确会稍微向上倾斜一下
When it separates from the second stage, it does sort of tilt down.
约110公里
但它还会继续飞到接近70英里的高空 才会往下坠落
But this thing will go almost 70 miles high before it finally starts coming down, falling from 70 miles.
当它掉进大西洋的时候 就直接摔烂了
When it hits the Atlantic, it pieces just go everywhere.
-粉身碎骨?  -是的
Bluey Yakubu going.
跟大家科普一下 火箭分离的目的是要把那些额外不需要的重量抛掉
To be clear, the reason you separate the rocket is you've got all this extra mass.
对 用过的东西一个不留
Right, trying to get rid of everything you've used.
当罐子里的燃料用完——
Once you're out of, out of all that fuel …
约2950吨
发射前 火箭总重量大约是650万磅
Sitting on the pad, we're about six and a half million pounds.
其实超过500万磅 约2280吨
而这枚火箭 它的一级就超过400万磅
This rocket, the first stage is like over 4 million pounds of that.
-哇  -一级真的是个庞然大物
Wow. The first stage is a big chunk,
2.2km/s
但它能把你一路送出大气层 加速到每小时5000英里
but it gets you up and get you up through the atmosphere and on your way up to 5000 miles an hour.
所以当你沿着它一路往上走的时候
So as you as you walk up beneath the thing, you'll see
你会发现有的地方光滑 有的地方是瓦楞板一样的波纹段
the smooth sections and corrugated sections.
我现在头顶这段就是光滑的
The smooth section directly above where I'm standing right now
-写着"USA"的地方 就是燃料罐  -OK
is the USA on it, is the fuel tank. Okay.
这里装的是煤油
So that's where the kerosene is.
约1.9cm
它是从厚度大约为四分之三英寸的铝板加工而来的
实际上各处厚度不一样
煤油罐厚度从下到上0.193-0.170英寸
液氧罐厚度从下到上0.254-0.190英寸
This thing is made out of aluminum plate, inch, insta inch and three quarter inch thickness.
从最初平展的铝板 在内表面铣出各种形状用于加强结构
这部分的详细内容可以查看
av718781179
They form a flat plate, they mill the inner surface for strength and some slosh baffling.
然后把铝板放入巨型压弯机中 给它压弯
And then they put this thing in a giant press and blend it.
形成一个 三分之一圆弧的铝片
Well, this plate is about is one third of the circumference.
然后把这些铝板竖起来 围成一个筒 自动焊接接缝
Then they take these plates, stand them up, and they have this automated welder.
我印象中 大概要走20到30个来回
As I recall, there was something like something like 20 to 30 passes
去焊接这些不到四分之三英寸厚度的铝板
to weld this inch and a half inch the quarter thick aluminum plate.
我记得那些技工聊过这些
I remember some of the mechanical guys talking about it.
他们会把这些先弄好
They would set the thing up,
做出测试件来
put up these what we call test coupons, just to, you know,
就是铝板的试样品 检查焊接是否合格
a piece of aluminum to check out the weld to make sure that's okay.
把做好的筒切开
So they make the wells and they take this thing, slice it up,
放在显微镜下观观察 然后告诉你
put it on the microscope, and they said, you
多数时候 很难能分辨出焊缝和原材料 真的超级超级精确
be hard pressed in most cases to tell the virgin aluminum from the well, they were very, very precise.
都是非常强的工匠
So they were super skilled craft.
-没错 没错  -太牛了
Yes. Yes. That's amazing.
对于波纹段来说 这些燃料箱…… 我得先讲一下背景
Corrugated sections, the tank now has to let me back up
火箭发动机……
The engines.
来自发动机的推力会沿着我们刚才走过的结构传递
The forces from the engines are transmitted out through the structure we were talking about.
所有力都会沿着箭体表面传递
And all the forces are transmitted upward through the skin.
火箭中央没有什么横梁之类的传力结构
There's no internal beams or anything like that.
所以所有力都是沿箭体表面传递的
So all your forces are going through the skin.
因此 燃料箱不但要承受垂直方向的力
Well, the tank now has to withstand the upward force,
还要承受燃料箱内的压力 即"环向应力"
plus the pressure in the tank called hoop stress.
-明白  -OK
Yes. Okay.
因此 相比于箱间段 燃料箱本身要承受更多的力
So the tank area is has to withstand more forces then do the inner tank areas.
所以箱间段可以使用这种波纹结构
箱体采用2219-Y87铝合金 密度2.84g/cm³
箱间段采用7075-T6铝合金 密度2.80g/cm³
So the inner tank areas are made with this corrugated material.
同时换用更轻质的材料 毕竟我只需要承受轴向的力
So I can use a lot lighter weight material because I'm only having to withstand upward force.
箱间段内部没有压力
I don't have any inside pressure.
哦 所以我的理解没错的话 有的话麻烦您指出一下
Oh, so. Well, correct me if I'm wrong on this, Luke.
比如那边 就是刚刚说的波纹段对吧
So right there I'm looking at the corrugated stuff, right?
它是因为有更多的横截面积 所以轴向能承受更大的力吗
It has a bigger cross section so that it can withstand more axial.
没那么复杂 就是做成波纹形状增加强度
Well, it's just no, it's just it just corrugated to give it more strength.
-不至于被压垮就行  -是的
So it's not going to buckle. Right.
那对于箱体内部来说 我发现这边
And so their tanks inside, like, am I looking?
这有个微缩模型 不知道它做得是否准确
So this is a model. I don't know if this is a correct model.
挺好的 这模型挺真实的
Yeah, it's a pretty good little model.
如果你观察下面这里的燃料箱
The if you look at the fuel tank is the lower section down here.
如果观察它的内部
If you look inside the tank,
"隧道管"
你会发现液氧管路是从燃料箱内部横穿过去的
you can see that the liquid oxygen lines actually run through the fuel tank.
约0.46米
直径大约18英寸
Those things about 18 inches in diameter.
如果设计成从箱体外侧走 就会打乱火箭表面的管路设计
If you had to bring them out around the tank, you would mess up
your streamlining on your rocket on your surface.
所以液氧隧道管设计成直接内穿燃料箱
So they're actually going through it.
而这里会遇到的问题是 液氧的温度会把煤油冻住
Now, the problem we have here is liquid oxygen would freeze the kerosene
所以这段管路结构更像是一个巨型的保温瓶
so that the piping that is going through there is kind of like a big thermos bottle.
您的意思是 上面这里是液氧箱
So you're saying like this is the this is the liquid oxygen tank.
-液氧在煤油的上面  -是的
So the oxygen set above the kerosene. Yeah.
而这里 两个箱体之前的管道
And these pipes that go in between the two.
-对  -这些管道看上去不小啊
Yeah. They, you've got these big pipes I guess.
-有几条这样的管路?  -5条 每台发动机一条
They sure do. How many are there. Five. For each engine.
-直接接过去吗?  -对
Just a direct line. Yeah. Okay.
然后我们还不希望管道表面有冻结的煤油
And so you want to make sure that you don't have frozen kerosene around that.
-所以它是设计成双层的吗?  -是的
So is double walled or how to do it. Yeah.
一个内层 一个外层 中间有低压的气体填充 跟保温瓶的结构一样
It has an inner wall outer wall and then it has a low
pressure gas in between, just like a thermos bottle, really.
用低压气体 因为它们隔热
And the purpose of the low pressure gas is insulation.
哇 懂了 第一次知道
Wow. Okay. Did not know this.
那这些隧道管下来后
And so when they came down
它们会从煤油箱出来 接到发动机顶端
then they come out and they go into the top end of the engine
而煤油管路直接从煤油箱底部出来
and the fuel lines now come out of the bottom of the fuel tank
这样每台发动机就有两条管路 一条燃料 一条氧化剂
and you have to look to fuel line for each engine.
每条各自进各自的泵
One go in each side of the pump.
发动机处理这些主要在顶端的涡轮
The the way the engine is organized on this thing is the top most turbine
顶部这里是液氧的入口
up near the top up here would be your liquid oxygen.
刚说的 18英寸的管线就直接进中间这个泵里
So the 18 inch line comes into the center of that pump
中间的就是液氧管路 进去后会分成两路
and then you have an oxygen line, go into the engine and go one on each side.
平衡发动机两侧的力
You're balancing the forces on your engine.
它下方的管路和泵 对应的就是煤油
Then the next line, the next pump down is the actual fuel pump.
而从燃料泵两侧进入的煤油最终会从这条管路进入发动机
And you have a line coming in the both sides of the fuel pump and then this line goes into the engine.
从体积上讲 它们混合比是怎样的?
So volume metrically. How does the chemistry work?
燃料更多还是氧化剂更多?
Do you have more fuel or more oxygen?
-氧  -氧更多一些 具体情况如何?
Oxygen. More oxygen, Yeah. So how does that.
你抬头看看
Where you look up here?
大概体积比是2:1
You've got a 2 to 1.
液氧是从哪里开始的?
Where does the oxygen start?
氧箱要往前走 箭体光滑段开始
Oxygen tank is in the smooth section up top up here.
我们现在头顶这个是煤油箱
Okay. One right above us was the fuel tank.
那个就是氧箱 能看出来 大概2:1
This now is the oxygen tank. You see that? About a two to one.
2:1 好的
Two to one. Okay. Wow.
然后 它们的密度很接近
And they density is about the same.
好的
Is it, okay.
大约1.141g/cm³
氢  呃不是 液氧大概是每加仑9磅
Hydrogen? I mean, oxygen is like 9 pounds per gallon.
大约0.82g/cm³
煤油我记得大约是每加仑7磅
Kerosene like seven, I think. Really?
-我们现在还在一级下面  -是的 还在一级下面
So we're still under stage one. We're still under the first stage.
那有个发动机 要去唠唠吗?
There's the engine. You talk about.
您想讲讲铬镍铁合金吗?
You talk about the inconel now.
看你意愿 你想聊聊那个喷注盘吗?
If you will, if you want to talk about that injector plate.
您别问我呀 您是向导 我听您的!
Well, I want you to talk about your more knowledgeable than I am.
我们之前说的喷注盘 就在这个发动机的喉部
Well, we were talking about the injector plate down in the throat of the engine.
喷注盘上面大约有5000来个孔
Is this injector plate got something like 5000 holes or something like that.
有的喷煤油 有的喷液氧
And some of the holes are spraying kerosene, some are spraying liquid oxygen.
喷注盘上有挡板
And you have these baffles
这台发动机最开始设计的时候 最开始是归空军研发的
when this engine was first made, the Air Force started development of this engine Early on.
他们当时认为核武器可能比想象中更笨重一点
They thought that nuclear weapons were going to be much heavier than they turned out to be.
所以他们打算研发一款重型运载火箭
So they thought they were going to need a heavy lift rocket.
他们想着送一个载人的空间实验室 搞些侦查活动之类的
They thought they were going to put manned orbiting laboratories spy in the sky type things.
最后发现技术上有点困难
And ultimately the technology got ahead of them.
所以这个发动机就交给了NASA 解决一些最后的难题后 用在土星火箭上
So this engine was transferred to NASA's to follow to
resolve the final issues and use it on the Saturn.
最开始没有那些挡板
Originally did not have the baffles.
问题是喷注盘喷出燃料后会开始旋转
The problem is this stuff spraying in here starts a circular rotating motion.
像一锅粥一样在里面转 转速能到2000RPM
So this gas starts circulating in this job like
we're talking about stuff swirling around, maybe 2000 RPM.
里面就很混乱
I mean, it's really moving in there.
问题是 这些喷注盘下
Problem you get with that is these injectors,
有些时候会混合 有时候混合得并不好
sometimes they mix, sometimes they don't mix well.
所以最后整个发动机就是
So you wind up you can get an engine that
一块区域可能氧太多了 煤油不够
I'm getting too much oxygen in an area, not enough kerosene.
最后会冲击钟形喷管的末端
It turns into settle and torsion cuts the end of the bell, really.
同样 还会有一块区域煤油太多 氧又不够
And then the other problem we have is if I get too much kerosene and not enough oxygen
这时候就像拖拉机上路一样突突突
in this thing, it starts like a car that's running rough on the road.
综合起来就是发动机的恶性的震动 会把自己震碎的那种
So now it starts a terrible vibration will shake it to pieces.
而这里的挡板 把之前的旋转分成了更多更小的区域
So the baffles break that swirling motion up into much smaller areas
让之前的效果不会那样明显
that then don't have such a major effect on it.
只要放几个挡板 燃料进入发动机主燃烧室的几英寸内
Once I put the baffles in and this is all happening in the first few inches of the injector.
图中纸面向外是发动机主燃烧室方向
First few inches into the engine of the injector.
这些挡板就足够解决问题了
So these baffles were enough to solve the problem.
我们测试了几种喷注盘设计 用于提高燃烧稳定余量
Several injector designs, such as this lock's dispersion injector,
have been tested in an effort to increase combustion stability margins.
包括多层同心圆形喷注盘
Other designs tested include the baffled divergent ring injector,
低燃料三角翼喷注盘
low fuel delta fin injector
21分区喷注盘
21 compartment baffled injector,
放射形同心圆喷注盘
and the divergent ring injector.
作为液氧与燃料隔离研究的一部分
As part of the LOX fuel isolation study,
我们已经在洛克达因的高流量试验台上进行了不同压力的测试
tests have been conducted on Rocketdyne's high flow test bench at varying pressures.
数据将进行评估 并与热试车结果进行比对
This data will be evaluated and compared with data from hot testing.
所以简单来讲 这些挡板就是在控制燃烧室内的巨型乱流
So so basically what they're doing is they're they're controlling
they're controlling a very huge turbulence problem right there.
它把乱流化整为零
They're cutting it into smaller chunks.
在每个小分区内就能有更充分的燃烧
And then that way you can get more complete mixing in these centers, right?
-侧面这个是您刚刚提到的小管路吗?  -对
Are these the pipes you were talking about here? Yeah.
这些就是铬镍铁合金管路 里面流的是冷却液
So these are the tubes inconel tubes where you're pumping the coolant.
围着一圈的这条粗管道 来自涡轮泵的废气
Now, this big baffle around this thing, we take the jet turbine,
发动机后面还有一段延伸的喷管 这里没有展示出来
there's a nozzle extension on the engine, which is not in this one,
沿着我指的方向 大约还有六七英尺的发动机喷管
laying alone side another six, seven feet of engine out here.
两部分的喷管 是由高强度不锈钢制造的
The two nozzle extension, well, it's made out of high strength stainless.
工程师们取富燃燃烧的涡轮泵的废气
And what they actually do is they take the turbine, exhaust the turbine now running a fuel rich mixture.
因为是富燃燃烧 所以废气只有1200度左右
So its exhaust temperature is only about 1200 degrees.
把废气的排气管围在这一圈
So by capturing that exhaust and routing it around here
对着延伸段的内壁排放废气
and then injecting an end to the walls of this nozzle extension
这一圈管子内壁有小孔
and then having little openings around the interior, the extension,
延伸段内壁的一层涡轮泵废气就是冷却延伸段的方法
the flow of that exhaust in the walls is how you're cooling the nozzle extension.
800度的《冷却》 可能有点抽象
Kind of hard to think of cooling with 800 degrees, but
但总比好几千度强
it's better than 5000. Wow.
而且当废气喷入排管内壁的时候
And then you allow the exhaust to be injected into the nozzle
还会朝喷的方向额外得到一点点推力
and that way you're extra thrust you're getting out of that is put in the direction you're going.
约8.2-9.1吨
产生大约18-20千磅的推力
That thing will produce about 18 to 20000 pounds of thrust.
如果往一侧排 还得费劲想办法平衡它
So if you squirted it out to the side, you forever be correcting with this.
冷却段是这18千磅推力吗?
The cooling section is 18,000 pounds?
就是涡轮的废气
Just the well, the exhaust from the turbine.
所以不然还得控制怎么排
So you have to control where.
我们直接就送进喷管里了
Your drive goes directed into the thrust chamber.
这样排的方向刚好和飞行方向对上了
So it's going in the direction you're going.
OK
Oh, okay.
Luke 您真是无所不知 我们永远追随您~
Luke, you're absolutely right. We could do this forever.
少跟我扯犊子
I don't know how you gonna cut this one.
xswl
So many fun.
终于见到二级啦
That's quite the reveal for stage two.
-赶紧讲完吧  -别别别 我很开心听您讲这些的
We'll we'll hustle. No, no, no. I like it. I'm having fun.
嗯 我们先说一级的顶部 就是地面支撑设备
Okay, Now we'll get to the top of this stage. We were talking about ground handling equipment.
看到顶部这个巨大的黄色结构了吧
You see this big yellow structure on the top of it.
它就是用来把火箭从运输载具上拎起来放到发射架上的
This is how you lift this thing off of the transporter and pick it up and put it on the launch pad.
然后黄色的这个支架就会撤走
Then you would remove this yellow structure up here
之后这里还有一个结构没有展示 从二级的底部开始
and then there's a piece missing that would go from the base of the stage
一二级级间段长18.25英尺 5.56米
大概在我站的地方 我记得大约有12-15英尺长
at about where I'm standing, I guess, 12 or 15 feet, something like that.
名字叫级间段
And this is an interstage.
一级顶部与级间段相连
Now the first stage attaches to the interstage.
如果这个东西……
The problem you have is if this thing were
如果二级直接和一级相连
if this stage were connected directly to the base,
记得刚刚说的 分离的时候一级会有一点翻转的倾向
remember we said when it separates, it really wants to flip up.
这样有可能刮到二级的发动机
Well, it would just rip the engine right off of this thing.
啊 所以需要想办法往回拉下面级?
I would suggest you have to pull it straight back.
对 你把它往后拽到一定位置的时候它就不会影响到我了
Well, you pull it back off or something back here? So if it moves like this, it will hurt me.
宇航员说过 有人问过他一次
The astronauts said that, some somebody asked him one time
我们之前在二三级分离上有点问题
we were having a problem with S-II S-IVB, the second third stage separation.
我们问他们 当时什么感觉?
We asked them, Well, what does it feel like?
那人说就好像火车脱轨了一样
Man, one of them said, man, that's like a train wreck that thing separated.
那这一二级分离又是什么感觉?
So well, what did this one feel like?
这个感觉就像巨型的火车脱轨了一样
This one felt like a large train wreck.
在那之后 偶尔你甚至可能在视频里听到
The astronauts after that, occasionally you listen to if you see one in the video,
他们正说话呢 突然一句"准备好要脱轨了" 说的就是火箭分离
you hear them talking, okay, here comes the train wreck, you know, and that's the separation
因为的确动静不小
because it bit it rattling around pretty good.
真的? 是因为瞬间的加速度吗?
Really? And it was the acceleration?
就是突然间分离 分离面火工品各种咣咣咣
Just the sheer separation of this thing, a lot of banging around when it comes to loose.
所以您和您的团队
So when you guys so you and your team, whoever whoever
控制火箭的点火 各种时序 等等
controlled the the the firing and the timing sequences and things like that.
发动机启动 烧完了这些燃料
So we've lit off the engines, we've burned all of our fuel
然后到了分离的时间
and it comes time to do separation.
是不是还要关掉……
So you have to shut the.
分离前要先关闭发动机
So you have to shut those engines down.
"MECO" 主发动机关机
MECO Main engine cutoff.
火箭发动机底部有四个小翼
And then there are four fins on the base.
小翼下面有整流罩 保护发动机在大气中摆动时不被大风吹到
Those fairing that flares out so that your engine, when you can gimlet
without the atmosphere streaking by and holding you, keep you from getting all right.
发动机整流罩上有小翼 一圈一共四个
And then in that fairing there is a fin. All right. Four of them around it.
在每个小翼的根部 有两台朝前的固体火箭
Well, at the base of that fin pointing in this direction, the two big solid rocket motor.
一圈一共就是八个
So there are eight of them around that thing.
火箭的一级通过火工品与级间段相连
EBW, exploding bridgewire, 爆炸桥丝
So the thing is connected to this interstage with a set of with a piece of ordnance.
计算机一看 该关机了 好 主发动机关机
So you computer says, all right, time to shut it down, main engine cut off,
火工品启动 把连接两边的张力带炸开
fires this ordnance this ordnance now separates the stages of strap together with tension straps
张力带内圈就是火工品 计算机下令炸开几组火工品
around the interior of those straps is the ordnance, computer fires the ordnance, several of these.
同时启动刚刚提到的反推火箭
Same time fires those retro rockets.
让一级部分减速 不会让它倒车 只是稍稍减速
To slow this thing down, doesn't back it up, just slows it a little bit.
这里没有展示的级间段
This piece that is missing up here, the interstage,
一圈还有八个固体火箭
there are eight more solid rocket motors around it
它们也会同时点火 推动上面的二级
and they're fired at the same time to put thrust on the upper on the second stage
为二级燃料沉底 并启动二级发动机
to keep the propellant seeded in the tanks and get these engines started.
-因为液体会往前晃动  -没错
Because of slosh. That's right.
必须让燃料在箱体内沉底
You got to get that stuff down in the tank.
不然发动机一关机 它们就会往前漂
Otherwise, when you shut off, they're just going to float forward.
所以需要一点点推力把燃料沉底 才能让发动机顺利启动
So you have to have a little bit of thrust to pull that stuff back and get these engines going.
二级发动机启动后 就可以抛掉级间段了
Once you get these engines going, then you jettison this interstage
从而抛掉多余的重量
and that's to get rid of excess weight.
所以一二级分离里面说道还真不少 我捋一捋 您看我说得对不对
So there's a lot more going on inside separation. Okay, So check me here.
-首先一级发动机关机  -嗯
So engines cut off. Yeah.
-然后炸开级间段与一级的张力带  -嗯
And then we blow the tension straps here. Yep.
-然后底部小翼上的四组反推火箭启动 给一级减速  -对
And then we have those four retro rockets on the fins. Fire those to slow this down. Right.
然后这里还要再推一把
And then we have a kick right here.
-上面这八个固推称为沉底发动机  -哦 OK
And we have these, these are called ullage rockets. Oh, okay.
轻轻推一下上面的部分 让燃料沉底
So we have a loose forward a little bit. Yeah. We'll kick in a
沉底后 启动这些发动机
Tank fuel, propellant tanks and then start these engines.
690吨
这些发动机……一级发动机 F-1 单台推力150万磅
Now, these engines first stage one and a half million pounds of thrust, F-1.
这些是J-2发动机
These are J-2 engines.
它的燃料是液氢 氧化剂当然还是液氧
The fuel here is liquid hydrogen and liquid oxygen, of course, oxidizer.
氢氧发动机的区别在于……
Now, the difference is engine.
有点长 你想听吗?
You want to go there?
我啥都想听!
Do I want to go everywhere
发动机有一个很重要的参数 叫"比冲"
You write these engine is by impulse, specific impulse.
如果用发动机的推力 除以 推进剂的流量
If you take the amount of thrust you're getting and divide that by the flow rate of your propellant.
多少磅的推力 除以 每秒多少磅的推进剂流量
How many pounds of thrust divided by how many pounds per second of stuff?
上面单位是"磅" 下面单位是"磅每秒"
If I take pounds, divide by pounds per second.
两个磅约掉了 单位就只留下一个"秒" 也就是比冲的单位
Do all that canceling stuff in ninth grade, algebra, whatever it was, you wound up with an answer in seconds.
比冲越高 发动机效率就越高
Okay, well, the more seconds you get, the more efficient you're in.
一级的发动机 也就两百出头 我忘记具体多少了
F-1发动机海平面比冲263秒 真空比冲304秒
Well, first stage engine efficiencies is down 200, and I don't remember the exact number.
就当225秒吧
We just say 225 seconds.
我们头顶这台 大约是425秒
J-2发动机真空比冲421秒
This engine is probably 425 seconds.
好高啊
That's high.
氢氧机效率非常高
So hydrogen gives you a lot more efficiency.
但是 小老弟 液氢这玩意可不好对付 零下250多度的东西
But, boy, hydrogen's, really tough to mess with 426 below zero.
一切操作都不一样了
So everything in all different world now for messing with
一瓶煤油放那啥事没有 液氢不行 但效率是真的高
a bottle of kerosene versus this stuff okay but more efficient
所以二级的发动机 每台……
so each of these engines now
刚刚提到一级发动机每台每秒消耗三吨的推进剂
the first stage remember we were burning three tons of propellant every second
690吨
产生150万磅的推力
to produce one half million pounds of thrust.
约272千克       约103吨
它们每台每秒消耗600磅的推进剂 产生23万磅的推力
These are burning about 600 pounds a second to produce 230,000 pounds of thrust.
约272千克
-每台每秒600磅?  -对
600 pounds a second? Yep.
约103吨
-产生多少推力?  -23万磅
To produce how much thrust? 230,000 pounds of thrust.
-每台大约100万磅的四分之一  -嗯
A quarter million per each of. Yep.
这五台发动机加一起差不多等于一级一台发动机
Okay, so this, these five engines equal about one of those first stage engine.
嗯 但是剩余的重量已经没那么大了
I see. But you have less mass that you're hauling around.
-没错  -我也不用带着一级那大家伙继续加速了
That's right. And so you don't have to accelerate all that.
而且我的燃料是液氢 密度非常低
I'm carrying hydrogen, which is pretty light hydrogen density.
大约1.141g/cm³
还记得我说的 液氧的密度大约每加仑9磅
Remember we said liquid oxygen is 9 pounds per gallon.
大约0.07g/cm³
液氢的话 每加仑大约只有0.7磅
Liquid hydrogen, 7/10 of a pound per gallon.
这个不同 导致这五台小发动机上面的氢泵需要转得非常非常快
The difference there means that these pumps on these poor little engines, they have to work really hard.
发动机上面的泵
The pumps that we were spinning,
约5500RPM
涡轮带动的泵 在一级发动机上转速大约是5000RPM
the turbine is spinning the pumps on the first stage engine at about 5000 revolutions per minute.
8600-8700RPM
J-2发动机的氧泵 大约是8000多RPM
The oxygen I believe the oxygen pump on this one is about 8000 RPM.
而它的氢泵 转速高达27000-28000RPM
老爷子可能记错了
数据来自维基百科等文献 已进行更正
And the hydrogen is 37,000 RPM.
氢泵转得飞快 因为液氢密度太低了 泵够快才能够量
They're working hard because hydrogen, the low density, it's got to work very hard to pump a bunch of that.
所以从体积上讲 泵需要工作非常快
So volume metrically, you're having to pump a lot faster
因为化学反应算的是质量 所以为了达到质量 对应的体积就非常大
because you have less mass, but you still need the same amount of
well, you need a lot of mass in order to make the chemistry work.
对 得从中获取能量呀
Yeah I got to get some oomph of that.
-技术交流  -有意思
Technical talk. That's amazing.
泵都在哪呀?
So where are the pumps?
每台都有自己的一套泵
So they're on each engine, each has its own.
五台发动机 外围四台可摆动 和一级的情况一样
So we have five engines here for outer engines are gimbal, just like first stage.
它们的话 一级是摆动5度
These I think first stage could move five degrees.
±7.0°
二级上的发动机我记得能摆动接近10度
I believe these would operate closer to ten degrees.
您的计算机仍然要控制这些?
And you're controlling these with your computer.
它们都在仪器舱的控制下 所有这些一切
These are all still under control of the instrument unit. Everything's under control.
我们一路走到这 一切都听仪器舱的命令
Everything we've talked about so far is under control of the instrument.
那您是怎么连接从计算机到……
Well, how do you connect the computer from.
就是说 仪器舱 在那头
So that means the instrument unit, which is over there.
在三级的顶端
At the top of the third stage.
在遥远的三级顶上
It's way up there, the top, the third stage.
那计算机是怎么连到……
How do you connect the computer.
-有线缆一路连着 从头连到尾  -它们在哪?
Cables going down, all the way down. Where would they be?
分级的地方能看到
They would be in going between the stages and you will see them all here.
级间段上
They are on the interstages.
上面还有分离插头
They have a they have disconnects.
还有备用的斩断的机构
And then they have a backup guillotine crack.
必须得把后面这玩意斩断 可不能晃荡根线还连着
Make sure that sucker's cut free, I don't want this like hanging on a cable.
-就像闸刀一样吗?  -咔嚓
So it's blade. You chooooop.
所以每一级都有独立的线缆与仪器舱连接
So and the stages are all connected through their independent lines from the instrument unit.
其实没那么多线 可能也就二三十根?
And they're not many lines. They're, you know, probably 20 or 30.
有意思
That's amazing.
那么这台发动机 叫什么来着?
And so this engine, what was it called?
J-2发动机
J-2. The J-2 engine.
火箭的二级和三级用的都是J-2发动机
Yeah, J-2 that would be on the second stage and the third stage.
-无数人倾尽毕生心血投入到了这台发动机上吧  -是啊
So a lot of people spent their entire lives just working on this engine. Oh, yeah.
是无数人倾尽毕生心血投入到这台发动机上的一个零件
A lot of people spent their entire lives working on one part of that engine.
-真的?  -大工程都这样
Really? It's kind of the way goes.
然后您出现了 研发计算机控制这一切
And then here you come along and you get to control everything.
-确实  -有意思
Right. That's amazing.
您的背后这个掌控一切的团队规模如何呀?
How big was your team that you worked on that would control everything?
IBM那边的话 最多的时候这边能有2000人吧
The IBM side here, I think the peak was about 2000 people here.
IBM在这负责制造计算机
The computer now was built by IBM.
然后纽约那边去了几百人吧我估计
And we go in New York several hundred I think probably.
具体多少人在干这个我不清楚
And I don't know how many of those actually worked on it,
但这个火箭上的每一个零件都是来自全国无数家公司
but now all the components on these things are come from companies all over the country.
IBM的工作就是负责统筹这些
So this IBM, our job was to put it all together.
我也做了点微小的工作
So I made some of it.
我们还买了不少这些公司的产品
We bought a lot of a lot of it comes from different companies.
你们是怎样管理……
How do you manage ……
今天我们有各种系统工程工具管理这些产品与它们的参数
Today we have systems engineering tools to manage all the parts and components and how they work.
在那个没有电脑的时代 你们是如何管理如此庞大的系统工程的?
How do you manage such a complex system in an era where there was no electronic bookkeeping?
NASA的……
NASA's
可能……
probably
每个零件 火箭的每一级 上面的每一个……接口
for every component, every stage, every interface.
NASA都有做好对应的接口控制文件
That was an interface control document that NASA produced.
OK
Okay.
当然 我们也会和部件的生产方合作
And course, we work with the company that whoever's making the component
他们会告诉我们 这些零件要用来做啥
and they say, here's what those components are going to do.
要有多大
It's going to be this big.
说白了 输入是什么 输出是什么
It's got these what the what we call the goes-intos and goes-outtas
信号入 信号出 功率多少
signals coming and signals going out this much power,
就那些东西 电压电流之类的 或者多大流量
you know, voltage or current or whatever, or fluid, if it's kind of, you know.
他们给每一个部件 每一级都做了接口控制文件
So they had an interface control document for every component, every major stage.
每次拿到一个接口 就能拿到它的接口控制文件
So every time you have an interface, you have this interface control document.
这样的安排非常妙
That was a stroke of genius.
我还清楚记得看这些文档的时候
I remember working with those interface control documents and
我能很快 很轻松地找到问题
it made it so much easier to understand a problem
因为文档写的很明白 好 他那边要这样的信号
because you could go to the document okay, here's what he signal he's going to get.
他要这样处理这些信号
Here's what he's going to do with it.
这里要啥 那里要啥
Here's what is going to get. Here's what it's going to do with it.
当你陷入这种不停解决问题的工作中时
So you were trying to do some problem resolution.
这些文档就是解决问题的良药 当然也可能会制造问题
Those things were great for solving problems as well as building them.
所以就是靠的接口控制文档吗?
So interface control documents were how to do it.
简称ICD 至少在我心中它们很妙 很有用
The ICDs we used to call them, they were they my mine were a stroke of genius.
-我们今天还在用  -没错 大家都是
We still use those today. Oh yeah. Everybody.
我觉得正因为有了它 整个项目才会如此成功
And that was I think that was really why this program was so successful.
真不错
Really. Okay.
-咱继续聊聊二级?  -好呀
You wanna talk about the S-II stage a little bit? Let's do it.
好 我们头顶这就是二级了
Okay. Well, above us is the S-II stage.
二级有一小部分的波纹段 但它大部分是光滑的
All right, now the S-II, we got a little bit of corrugated, but most of it is smooth.
还记得吗 在一级上我们有煤油箱 还有液氧箱 它们是两个分开的罐体
So in the first stage, remember, we had the hydrogen, we had the kerosene tank,
and then we had the liquid oxygen tank and a two totally separate tanks.
而在二级这里 两种燃料的储箱采用了共底设计
Here we have a deal where there's a common bulkhead between the two tanks.
这样可以节省大量的箭体长度 从而节省大量重量
That saves a tremendous amount of length, which saves a tremendous amount of weight.
什么是(共)底?
What's a bulkhead?
二级不是串联两个半球底储箱
I don't have a I don't have a hemispherical tank here. And then another one up here.
而是一个储箱内有一个半球底 它同时作为下面氧箱和上面氢箱的底
Actually, I've got one surface and that's surface serves the oxygen tank below in the hydrogen tank above.
所以不是两个完整罐体 而是像三个隔板一样?
So I get to instead of having a tank like this and a tank like this, I just have three.
没错
That's right. Okay.
的确分成了氧箱和氢箱 但它们共用一个半球形的底
I've got an oxygen tank and a hydrogen tank, but they share one of the
one of the bulkheads of the tank is shared.
OK
Okay.
共底一侧是液氢 一侧是液氧
So we have hydrogen on this side, oxygen on that side.
这样会为火箭节省很多长度
Well, that saves a lot of length on your rocket, on your stage.
从而节省很多重量
And by doing that, you're saving a lot of weight.
减重很重要
So that's very important.
我记得这个想法提出比一级火箭的提出晚了很多 当时是……
And so that was an idea that came along long after S-IC stuff, I guess, that's been done on the...
那您……抱歉我不太懂这方面
So if you have a forgive my ignorance here,
我在想的是一个半球底的燃料罐 就像后院储气罐那样
so I'm imagining it like a propane tank, you know, like behind your house.
两侧是半球形的 中间是圆柱形的
Yeah, you've got a hemisphere on each side and you've got a cylinder in the middle,
是的
Right.
如果我在一侧再加一个燃料罐
So if I stuck another propane tank on the back side
把圆柱的部分连接起来
and I had the cylinder and it connected,
共底的一侧会有一段锐角一样的死角吧
there would be a little a little sharp point on the corners.
我应该说清了吧
It might make it any sense.
所以共底储箱 一侧是下面的底
So basically I got a hemisphere this way.
假设我们在往左射火箭
Let's say we're shooting a rocket that way.
储箱一个下底 一个上底
You got a hemisphere on the back and I get a hemisphere on the front.
中间的共底部分 穹顶是凸向哪边的?
That one in the middle. Is it facing this or this way?
[指向飞行方向]
OK 指向火箭顶端
Okay. Pointy end up.
发射火箭第一条规则 往上飞
Rule #1 in flying a rocket, keep the pointy end up.
OK 懂了
Okay, That's awesome.
我们抬头看看头顶的二级
Okay, so now this stage you can see above us up here,
可以发现表面有点奇怪
it has sort of a funny looking surface to it.
它表面是用泡沫填充的酚醛蜂窝网格
This was a phenolic honeycomb grid, and then it was filled with foam.
约-253°C
装液氢的燃料罐非常…… 液氢温度太低了 零下426华氏度
The hydrogen tank is so.. hydrogen is so cold, 426 below zero.
需要做好隔热 做非常非常严密的隔热
You really have to insulate it and you have to insulate it very, very good.
如果不做隔热 它沸腾的速度可能比燃料加得还要快
Problem you run into is if you don't insulate that tank,
the boil-off from it will be so great that you can't fill the tank.
所以为了加注 首先就必须做好隔热
So you got to insulate it to fill it number one.
更不用说为了让它储存一段时间
Plus you got to insulate to make sure it lasts any time.
二级火箭是在箱体外部做隔热的
So the second stage is insulated on the outside.
这种酚醛网格隔热是早期几次发射中使用的
This was used on some of the early flights, this phenolic deal.
之后 我记得就换成大的聚苯乙烯泡沫直接贴在表面了
Later on, my understanding is they went to like big styrofoam blocks just glued to the outside.
效果更好一点
It worked a lot better.
对于上面级 它会工作……
Upper stage now, the upper stage will last
一级工作两分半
first stage we were burning two minute, two and a half minutes.
而二级会工作大约6分钟
This one's going to burn about 6 minutes.
OK
Wow. Okay.
所以其实一二级并不会飞多久
So not long into the flight, these two stages are gone.
而对于三级 它是要跟着入轨的
But the third stage now, he's going to go in orbit
所以在三级分离前 它可能要飞行数个小时
and it's going to be a number of hours before we're through with it.
所以它的隔热是在箱体内侧做的
It's actually insulated on the inside of the tank.
-真哒?  -嗯
Really? Yeah.
OK 液氢……哪个在上面?
Okay. So hydrogen, which one's on top?
-液氧还是……?  -液氢在上面
Oxygen or...? Hydrogen's on top.
液氢的箱体非常大
Hydrogen's the big tank.
然后液氧在下面
And then the oxygen below.
因为化学反应方程是那么写的
And that's just because of the stoichiometry of the chemical equation,
……之类特拽的词
whatever the fancy word is.
其实只是想把重量往下放
Well, you put most of the weight in the bottom.
-原来如此  -我个人认为啊
I see.  I think.
OK 有道理的
Okay, that makes sense.
于是我们来到了 二级的顶端
Okay. Now, when you come to the end of the second stage,
三级的起始部分 这里还是有个没有展示出来的级间段
beginning of the third, we've got another interstage and of course it's missing here.
你可以在那边的模型上看到
You can see it on the model over there.
10米
这里有一个缩窄的部分 一级二级箭体直径33英尺
So there's a tapered section that goes... the first two stages are 33 feet in diameter.
而三级与仪器舱直径22英尺 最上面的飞船直径11英尺
This third stage and the instrument unit are 22 feet in diameter and the spacecraft is 11 feet in diameter.
上头知道火箭是由不少咱们阿拉巴马人参与制造的
阿拉巴马州教育水平位居全美倒数
所以有"这里的人很笨"的刻板印象/地域黑
老爷子这里是算是一种自黑 视频中两人都是阿拉巴马人
They knew they're going to be a lot of us Alabama guys working on it.
所以干脆设成33 22 11 让他们更好记
So 33, 22, 11 they were keeping it simple.
这段还是掐了别播了哈哈哈哈
You don't have to put that in there.
当然了你们的意见也是很重要的!
Somebody did make a decision though, didn't they?
在三级上面 只有一台发动机
So now when we get to the third stage, we've only got one engine.
OK
Okay.
之前的一级和二级 都有四台外侧发动机
Well, before, first two stages, we've got four outer engines
可以通过摆动发动机实现火箭的俯仰 偏航 滚转
that we can gimbal those and we can make the rocket pitch,
we can make it yaw, and we can make it roll.
而三级只有一台发动机 只能实现俯仰和偏航 无法滚转
With one engine I can pitch and I can yaw but I can't make it roll.
有意思
Interesting.
所以火箭上的两个黑色东西 一个在右边 一个在左边 可能看不太清
So the two black pods. There's one up here on the upper right.
There's one on the left. Probably can't see it.
它们是一组推进器 在发动机工作时提供滚动控制
There's a set of thrusters in there to give us roll control while the engine's burning.
它们叫什么? RCS吗?
What's that called? Is that called a reaction...
辅助推进系统 APS
This is called the auxiliary propulsion system, APS.
OK
Okay.
它们是接触自燃型的 知道吧
These are hypergolic, you know,
四氧化二氮和…… 随便一个还原剂吧 比如肼
nitrogen tetroxide, whatever that other stuff is, hydrazine. Hydrazine.
两种组元的燃料喷入燃烧室时
And so when they when they squirt it into the chamber
会瞬间自燃 就不需要点火装置了
it immediately burns, you don't have to have an igniter.
所以在点火期间 APS会为火箭提供滚动控制
So during the boost phase, they have the APS gives you the roll control.
三级会跟着入轨并滑行一段时间
Now this will go into orbit and will coast.
而在滑行段 APS上面还有俯仰和偏航推进器进行姿态控制
And while we're coasting there are roll pitch and yaw thrusters in there to control it.
这也是由您控制的吗?
And you're controlling those?
它们都是由仪器舱控制的 没错
This all under control of the computer, instrument, right. Wow.
一级在40英里左右高空关机 分离 继续往上飞一会掉回大海
So the first stage shutdown at about 40 miles high and then it went on up
higher and then fell into the ocean,
700多公里
会落在离卡角约450英里的大西洋
wound up about 450 miles from the Cape in the Atlantic.
他们会提前发航警信息 防止砸到渔船之类的
They put out maritime warnings, you don't want that thing to fall on your boat while you're out there fishing.
当二级发动机关机的时候 一级还在往上飞
The second stage now, he shuts down. The first stage was still climbing.
185km    25000km/h 6900m/s
而二级 大约会在115英里高空 时速15500英里
This one now, he's up to about 115 miles high, traveling 15,500 miles an hour.
之后会直接扎进大气中
He's going to do a nosedive into the atmosphere.
进入大气后可能会在某个高度解体
Going into the atmosphere, probably begins to break up at altitude.
4000多公里
不会烧光 但会解体 碎片会掉在离卡角2000-2500英里远的地方
It doesn't burn up, just breaks up and pieces in the neighborhood
of 2,000 miles, 2,500 miles from the Cape, something like that.
-哇  -掉进大西洋
Wow. In the Atlantic.
而三级会再工作大约两分钟
Okay. Now the third stage is going to burn for about 2 minutes.
它会把火箭带到……
Okay. Now he's going to take them up.
188公里  超过28000km/h 7800m/s
不会很高 大约117英里 速度每小时17500英里
Not much higher, 117 miles high, probably 17,500 miles an hour puts them in orbit.
现在问题是 或者说情况是这样的
Now, the problem we have here, or the situation,
我们要去月球 但我们是从卡角发射的
we're going to the moon, but we launch from the Cape.
卡角在地球上
Cape is here on the earth.
从卡角只能往某个特定方向发射
You launch you can only launch in certain directions from the Cape.
嗯
All right.
所以我们先发射进一个近地轨道
So what you do is you, you launch and you wind up in an orbit above the earth,
但轨道面和月球公转轨道不同
but the orbit plane is in a different plane from the plane of the moon that's also orbiting the Earth.
所以我们进入近地轨道后 先关机 滑行一圈半
All right, so we go into orbit, we shut this thing down, usually coast an orbit and a half.
在电池用完之前可以滑行最多6小时
We could have coasted as much as 6 hours before we batteries ran out.
但通常是滑行一圈半 一两小时的时间
Usually only orbit and a half, hour and a half or so, 2 hours.
我们要做的是等滑行到 我们的轨道与月球的公转轨道平面相交时
And what we do is when our orbit we come around in our orbit
and it intersects the plane of the moon's orbit,
重启这台发动机
we restart this engine again.
所以这台发动机一共会进行两次点火
So this one burns twice.
第二次点火会持续6分多钟
Now he will burn for about 6 minutes.
将火箭带离原有的轨道面 去匹配月球的轨道面
It will take them out of the moon's plane, I mean, out of his orbit plane and into the moon's orbit plane
接近40000km/h 10.9km/s
并加速到每小时24500英里
and up to 24,500 miles an hour.
正式开始奔月
Now they're on their way to the moon.
之后 船箭分离 宇航员开始干他们的活了
And after that, crew's got to get separated and do all their magic.
-你想听的话我们一会可以聊聊  -想听想听
Okay. So we'll talk a little bit about that if you want to. Let's do it.
三级火箭最后怎么处理了?
Where do you get rid of the third stage?
它会跟宇航员一起去月球吗?
What I mean, does it go to the moon with you?
这个我稍后会讲 非常好的问题
Oh, we'll get back to that one. That's a good one.
我们不花太长时间讲飞船的部分 简单讲讲 它在这个地方
We won't spend much time on the spacecraft, we'll just say, here's here's where it is.
哈哈哈 我们不讲太多去月球的部分 包括实际登月的部分
Yeah, we'll just we won't talk much about the little thing that went to the moon.
Like the actual land part.
想听的话你可以去林顿·约翰逊航天中心
If you will know about that, go to the Johnson Space Center.
这应该是这里最好的微缩模型了
Here's here's probably the best little thing you can show is this,
这个模型展示了三级 仪器舱
this model here shows the third stage, the instrument unit,
仪器舱上面是登月舱适配器 简称SLA 登月舱就在里面
and the lunar module is inside what's called a spacecraft lunar module adapter, the SLA.
再往上是服务舱
And then the service module atop that.
再往上是指令舱
And atop that is the command module.
三个宇航员发射时就在指令舱内
And this is where the three astronauts are located.
指令舱上方 火箭顶端是发射逃逸系统
Now, this launch escape system up here on top of it,
如果在一级工作的时候想要中止发射
if we had to abort during the first stage burn,
比如挂了两台发动机 或者一级发动机摆动幅度过大
we lost two engines or the rates got too high,
如果发动机摆动幅度过大 火箭会解体
if the rates get too high on that first stage, you can break this thing in two also.
在这些紧急情况下 就要尽快逃离火箭
So that is an emergency, get them off of there right now.
所以在仪器舱内有紧急情况监测系统的硬件
So there's an emergency detection system, hardware in the instrument unit.
这里不需要计算机参与
We don't need the computer. We don't need any of this.
全是硬件线缆连接 三冗余
It's all hard wired. It's triple redundant and everything.
如果一级有两台发动机故障
So if I lost two engines on that first stage,
系统会自动启动逃逸塔内的发动机
that system would automatically fire a rocket motor that's in that launch escape tower up there.
逃逸塔会把指令舱 连带着里面的宇航员拽离火箭
That thing would pull just the command module with the crew.
And you know, the crew members are inside, the astronauts are inside there.
9-12km
无论何时发生故障 逃逸塔都会把他们带离大约三万到四万英尺更高的地方
So this thing now would pull them wherever the abort occurred, would take them 30,000 to 40,000 feet higher.
之后指令舱和逃逸塔分离 并利用降落伞返回
Then they would jettison and they would come down on their parachutes.
这一切只可能会在一级工作时发生
That's only in first stage burn.
我现在在看这里 有几个向下的喷口
I'm looking at it right there so I can see the nozzles on the back side.
-它们是发动机?  -对 固体火箭发动机
So that's a rocket. Solid rocket motor yup.
-而喷口是朝向四周的  -没错
And nozzles are pointed out. That's right.
是为了防止烧到指令舱顶部?
And that's to not burn the top of the gumdrop.
对 别把飞船烧了
Don't melt.. Yeah, don't melt the spacecraft.
飞船在那段时间内
Now, the spacecraft during that point,
在飞船上升的时候 为了应对可能出现的逃逸
as they're going up in, in case you were to have an abort that
发射逃逸系统其实在指令舱顶部有一个罩子
Boost Protective Cover(BPC) 逃逸推进保护罩
launch escape system actually has a cover that is actually over the top of the spacecraft.
在二级发动机点火 逃逸塔分离前 指令舱窗外是什么都看不见的
Until they jettison this during second stage burn, they can't hardly see anything.
指令舱侧面有个小窗户能看到外面
这个小窗位于指令舱左侧对接窗(left CM rendezvous window)上
直径8英寸
There's a little window down at the side they can see out.
但最大的是挡住的 看不到外面
But the main one, they can't. It's covered
保护罩可以在不得不启动逃逸发动机的时候保护飞船
and that's in case we had to fire that thing, we wouldn't damage the spacecraft.
有意思
Yeah, interesting.
而抛逃逸塔的时候 逃逸塔会带着锥形的保护罩一起分离
And when the launch escape tower separates, it pulls that conical section with it as part of it.
什么时候点火? 我是指抛逃逸塔的时候
So when does that fire? I mean you've got to get rid of it.
二级的时候 二级刚点火就抛掉
During second stage, just after the second stage burn starts.
OK 所以是在一级之后
Okay, so it's after first.
-在二级点火的时候抛逃逸塔?  -是的
So you jettison it while you're firing the second stage? Yes.
真的啊 我之前从来没想过
Yes. Really? Yeah. Okay. I didn't realize that.
逃逸塔的最顶端还有一个小发动机
It has it has a little motor up at the front of it
可以在逃逸塔工作时让其偏离火箭飞行方向
that will, will pull it away and pitch it up out of the flight path.
所以顶部还有一个小发动机
So there's a little motor on top of it.
对 上顶端内部还有一组小的辅助发动机
Yeah. There's a couple of little extra auxiliary motors inside that
-上面的火箭很笨重吧? 是固推吗?  -对 固体火箭
Is it a pretty dumb rocket up there? It's solid, right? Yeah, it's solid.
那玩意推力不小呢 和整个红石火箭差不多 只是工作时间很短
That thing has as much thrust as a Redstone rocket. Just doesn't burn as long.
所以它会迅速把指令舱带离 G值可不小
It'll snatch them away there real quick, they will pull some Gs.
-真的?  -真发生时里面的人可不好受
Really? Probably be sore if that ever happened.
幸好从来没用上过
Luckily, we never had that happen.
真棒
That's amazing.
我从来没想过它还要抛掉 是叫jettison吧?
I did not realize that you jettisoned that. Is that the word jettison?
我之前不知道是在二级工作过程中抛掉的
I didn't realize you jettisoned that while the second stage was burning.
嗯 二级刚点火不久就会抛掉
Just after second stage, you start burning, then you get rid of it.
-哦 二级之后?  -二级点火之后
Oh, just after second stage. Just after it starts.
-OK  -二级开始工作 就抛掉逃逸塔
Okay. Yeah, it just started burning. Then you toss that thing.
接下来就是仪器舱了 提过几次了
Now the the instrument unit, we talked about it.
它位于三级的顶端
This is where it's located on top of the third stage.
此时此刻 我们会……
When the, when we get to this point, we will just…
登月舱此时位于这段收窄的部分内部
The lunar module is inside the tapered section up here.
顶部的逃逸塔也早已抛掉了
We've jettisoned that launch escape tower, so it's no longer there.
而指令舱和服务舱会一直连在一起
The command module and the service module are going to stay together
直到返回地球再入大气前才会分离
until just before they re-enter the Earth's atmosphere coming home.
此时火箭和飞船正在飞向月球
So at this point now they're heading toward the moon
1000多公里
可能离地也就600-800英里吧 还不是很远
where, you know, we're probably 600 or 800 miles above the earth, not very far yet.
他们需要大约三天飞到月球
They've got about three days to get to the moon.
此时 指令舱和服务舱一起
So the crew now, the command module, service module together,
会和登月舱适配器(SLA)分离
they will separate from this launch escape from the the SLA, the spacecraft Lunar module adapter.
分离后 飞离火箭一小段 然后调转180度
They will separate and move away from the space from the rocket, and then they'll turn around.
转身的时候 我们会把登月舱适配器的四片整流罩分离
As they're turning around, we'll jettison four panels on this SLA here,
当然这也是仪器舱负责控制的
which is part of the instrument unit control stuff again.
它会下指令抛掉四片整流罩
Center command will jettison these four panels.
此时登月舱底部仍与登月舱适配器相连
That leaves the lunar module still attached to this lower part of the SLA
而登月舱顶部会朝前暴露在外
with the top end of the lunar module pointing forward,
指令舱服务舱分离后 转身 飞回来 和登月舱顶部对接
the command module goes out, turns around,
comes back and docks with the top part of the lunar module.
对接 设定好 连接一些线缆和插销
They dock and then they will set up, hook up some cables and some latches
然后指令舱上按下一个开关 让登月舱和火箭分离
and they throw a switch in the command module and that releases the lunar module from the rocket.
然后他们就开始飞向月球
Now they're going on their way to the moon.
假如月球是我左手 他们在我右手这里 还要飞三天
Now the moon's up here. They're down here three days away almost.
"他们"指的是飞船 月球此时是向左公转的
They, they the spacecraft. Moon's moving like so.
他们的轨迹会直奔月球公转方向前侧的边缘部分
They will follow a trajectory and go around the leading edge of the moon,
之后服务舱发动机点火 把他们带入近月轨道
fire that service module, engine'll slow them down, put them in orbit.
然后他们干他们的活 之后再靠服务舱发动机离轨返回
Do their thing, and then they use the service module to get away.
接近40000km/h 10.9km/s
当三级第二次关机的时候 我们速度大约是每小时24500英里
Now, when we shut down the stage, we're going 24,500 miles an hour.
我们离地只有几百英里
We're only a few hundred miles above the Earth.
地球重力会很快让它们减速
The Earth's gravity is slowing them down very quick.
船箭分离的时候 每小时能减速大约12000-14000英里/小时
By the time the crew separates this thing is probably
everything is probably slowed down to maybe 12,000, 14,000 miles an hour
因为我们里地球还很近
because you're still very close to the earth.
地球母亲一直在说"快回来吧宝贝"
Earth's gravity saying, come on back home guys.
而当船箭分离的时候
So this thing now when they separate,
11-13km/h 3-3.5m/s
下面的火箭会减速大约每小时7-8英里
they would slow this we'd slow this stage down maybe seven miles an hour, eight miles an hour.
同时还会让上面的飞船加速个几英里每小时
They would speed up the spacecraft a few miles an hour.
原因是它的惯性太大了 如果不想办法给它减速
And the reason is so much momentum with this, if we did not slow this stage down,
那么在他们飞到月球之前 三级火箭很有可能会撞上飞船
there was a very high probability that before they could reach the moon,
the S-IVB stage would run into the spacecraft.
所以这是一个安全措施
Oh. Okay, so this was a safety...
所以它们会以某种编队一样往前飞吗?
So they were flying, they may be flying a formation like that?
毕竟你们都是往一个地方飞的 总要做一些防撞措施
Well, you're going you know, you're going to the same place if you don't do something.
所以我们会让……会有这样的安全措施
So we would make... that was a safety measure.
是用什么减速的? 哪里的发动机吗?
How would you fire it? Where were the rockets at?
就用那边的辅助推进系统APS
That's that auxiliary propulsion system back there.
那边小小的黑色装置吗? OK
The little black thing right there? Okay.
这样的机动完成后
Now, once we had done that maneuver
一切安排妥当后 基于任务需求
and everything was okay, now, depending on the mission,
在早期的任务中 我们会重新调整三级的姿态
the early missions, what we would do then is we would actually reorient the stage,
排出箭体内剩余的少量燃料
pump some propellant out the back of it that's left, a little bit of propellant left.
不是发动机点火 只是把燃料排出去 启动几个小推进器
Don't fire the engine, just pump it out of it, fire some thrusters.
月球是我左手 我们现在在减速
And the moon's up here. So we'll slow it.
比如说我们现在速度是每小时12000英里
We're going let's say we're going 12,000 miles an hour.
137km/h 38m/s
我们只需给它减速85英里每小时
We slow this thing 85 miles an hour out of 12,000.
就会让它变成从月球公转方向的后侧擦肩而过
It will go around the trailing edge of the moon.
蓝线是登月舱指令舱服务舱组合体轨迹
黄线是三级火箭与仪器舱绕月轨迹
红线是其撞月轨迹
三级与仪器舱走哪条轨迹
取决于APS点火时间
(非真实比例)
真的?
Really.
3200公里
最近能飞到离月球2000英里 而月球的引力会把它甩进绕日轨道
We get within 2,000 miles of the moon, the moon's gravity now throw this in orbit around the sun.
所以现在有5枚这样的三级火箭正在绕太阳飞
So we got five of these orbiting the sun. Right now? Right now.
从阿波罗12号任务开始 宇航员会在月表留下一组设备
Now, beginning with Apollo 12, the astronauts would leave the instrument packages on the moon
称为"阿波罗月面实验装置" ALSEP
called Apollo Lunar Surface Experiment Package, ALSEP.
阿波罗计划的科学目标之一是确定月球的内部一致性如何
One of the objectives of one of the science objectives of Apollo
was to determine what the interior of the moon... what's the consistency?
月球有没有像地球那样炽热的内核
Do we have, does it have a molten core like the Earth?
它的核心是连续一致的密度 还是也有一个核心? 后来发现的确有
Is it sort of like a consistent density, or does it have mass concentrations? Which it turns out it does.
所以从阿波罗12号开始 之后每次着陆他们都会留下一套ALSEP装置
So beginning with Apollo 13, after 12, and every time they land, they leave an ALSEP package.
137km/h 38m/s
所以在阿波罗13号任务中 我们没有给它减速85英里每小时
So at Apollo 13, instead of slowing at 85 miles an hour,
72km/h 20m/s
而是减速45英里每小时 让它最终撞击月球
we slow it 45 and slam it into the moon.
这东西撞月的能量大约相当于10-11吨的TNT
This thing hitting the moon is about somewhere around 10 to 11 tons of TNT.
造成了一场持续2.5到3小时的月震 撞得不轻呢
What? Create about a 2.5 to 3 hour moonquake. It'd rattle it pretty good.
你想象上面小绿人吓的乱跑 "美国佬又来啦"
All the green men are running around. Oh man, the Americans are back.
-所以应该叫月震对吧 不是"地"震  -没错
It would be a moon quake wouldn't it? Yes, yes, that's right.
不是地震 是月震~
It's not an earthquake. It's a moonquake.
所以您的计算机会控制APS进行点火
And so so the computers that you controlled to fire that package, the APS right there.
所以这台发动机 控制那边的APS
So this computer would control that APS.
让它不要进行85英里每小时的速度增量的点火 而是多少来着 45?
And instead of 85 miles an hour deceleration, you give it, what did you say 45?
实际控制的是点火时间
Just how many seconds do I burn.
所以会有一个这样的对话 上面找到你们计算机团队
And so there was a conversation, Hey, computer team,
-我们想点火多久多久 让它坠毁在月球上  -没错
we need you to fire this much so we can slam this into the moon.
这些其实都是预先规划好 编程好的
Yeah, these were all preprogramed and preplanned.
在滑行期间和地月转移期间
Now, during the coast period and during this trans-lunar coast period,
任务中心可以给它发指令让它多工作一会或少工作一会
Mission Control could send commands up to make it burn longer, make it burn less.
懂吧 都是可以改的
You know, they could make some changes.
点火的时候就不能改了 只能在地上静静坐着看了
Didn't change anything during during boost, the ground is sitting there watching
但入轨之后 就能有很多可以修改的地方
but once you get into orbit and on your way you can do various things with it.
马歇尔太空飞行中心在这里有一个小组 行星科学家Renee Weber博士
There's a group here at Marshall, Renee Weber, Dr. Renee Weber.
她是负责月球……呃 不对 太空物理那部分的吧
Lunar... no, not lunar... Space Physics Division, something.
OK
Okay.
几年前他们调出一组当时撞击的一些数据
They went back a few years ago and retrieved all this old data from these impacts. Okay.
当年这些数据噪声很大 那年代电子器件 你懂得 数据噪声
Originally the data is pretty noisy, electric, you know, data noisy.
所以当时的人看完数据 说月球可能有个炽热的核心吧 但不确定
And they said, well, it appears that there was there is a molten core, but we're not sure.
而Weber博士和她的团队 大概在八九年前吧
Well, Dr. Weber and her team, maybe eight or nine years ago,
调取了当年那些旧的数据 利用现代信号处理技术进行处理
went back and retrieved all this old data, cleaned it up with the modern signal processing techniques
得出结论 月球的确有一个炽热的核心
and determined, yes, there is a molten core,
有一个富含铁的固态核心 类似于地球
there's an iron-rich, solid core, kind of like the earth.
核心表面有一层炽热的物质
Then there's a molten core around that.
而月球核心还有一层 不是那么高温 也不完全是固体的物质
But the moon has an extra layer that's not quite molten and not quite solid yet.
月球正在变冷 他们的理论就是这样
The moon is cooling. The theory is that the moon is cooling.
对于地球来说 我们的地核仍然因中心的放射性物质而保持炽热的状态
In the case of the earth, our molten core is kept molten
by radioactive materials in the center of the earth.
所以地球的核心相比而言更加……稳定
So the earth molten core's kind of static.
因为磁场的作用吗?
The magnetic field has something to do with..
很多因素 这是很多因素共同作用的结果
A lot of that. Yeah. Yeah. You know, all that stuff ties together.
对于月球来说 它的核心在变冷
The case of the moon, the moon is cooling.
所以刚刚说的额外的那一层 就是还没冷却下来的部分
And so this extra layer is part that hadn't quite turned to solid yet.
如果倒退个 比如说几百万年
If you go back another, you know, million years from now,
可能会发现那个核心比现在更小
it will be smaller, the molten core.
这个真有意思
So... That's amazing.
月球核心没有那种放射性物质
It doesn't have the molten... doesn't have the radioactive material.
这个实验真的很奇怪啊 谁想出来的
That's a very odd experiment that somebody came up with.
一拍脑袋 灵光一闪
I know, guys. Yeah.
您觉得会不会是这样 大家正讨论该怎么办呢
Do you think it was one of those things where they're like, What do we do with it?
突然有人说 把火箭砸月球上怎么样
Well, maybe we just crash it in there and.
不不 你说这就是ALSEP的内容之一
Well, no, that was part of the ALSEP design was the, you know, the
其中一个科学目标就是研究月球的内部
one of the science objectives was to determine the interior of the moon.
所以作为ALSEP的内容之一 就把这项加进去了
And so part of the ALSEP design was to add this.
作为一个次要目标
Like a secondary.
放个地震仪
Seismometer.
懂了 有意思
Yeah. That's amazing.
您看到这个东西的时候
Okay, So, so when you look at this thing right here,
这台计算机 环形的仪器舱 对吧
so this is the computer, the instrumentation ring, right?
嗯 这应该是一个模型 不是真家伙
Yeah. Yeah. This is a kind of a mockup of it. This is not really.
看着它的时候 您有什么感觉?
What do you feel when you see this?
我有什么感觉?
What do I feel?
没感觉?
Nothing.
呃 的确我曾研发过它吧
Yeah, I've been there before.
嗯 就是…… 你懂吗
Yeah, Yeah. Well, it's, it's. You know,
能勾起我很多美好回忆吧 因为它……
it brings back a lot of good memories. I know that because this was uh...
很多人都是大学才刚毕业就参与进这个项目了
So many of us that came in to work on this program were right out of college.
所以从来没有人有过任何经验
So this is something that nobody had ever done before,
而这是一个极好的学习经历 因为……
and it was a great learning experience because there were...
它涉及太多太多不同的领域了
there's so many different aspects to it.
你知道吧 各种技术部门
You know, technology goes from, you know,
比如搞射频的 要负责把数据传回地面 还有遥测系统 等等
the RF technology to transmit the data to the ground, the telemetry systems and so forth,
还有环境控制系统
the environmental control system。
实际上在60年代 我们没有那么多的计算机资源
And the fact that we, in the 1960s, we didn't have a whole lot of compute power.
当时有一个数字计算机和模拟计算机
So we have a digital computer and an analog computer.
OK
Okay.
而这是IBM在泰坦导弹上所做工作的一个延伸
And this was an outgrowth of what had been done on the Titan missile that IBM had done.
我们把两者结合了起来
So we had this combination.
数字计算机负责导航与制导
So the digital computer does navigation and guidance
包括所有时序 发动机启停 反推点火
and all those timing things, start engine, stop engine, fire retros,
启动分离火工品 分离登月舱适配器整流罩
fire all this ordnance, and you know, blow the panels off the SLA,
所有这些类型的离散功能都交由数字计算机完成
all of those kinds of discrete functions were done in the digital computer.
生成计算机字符 通过遥测发给地面 也是数字计算机完成的
Generating a computer word to telemeter to the ground is done in the digital computer.
导航与制导也是数字计算机的活
And navigation and guidance is done in the digital computer.
但控制下面那台发动机 当时世界上用的都不是数字的
But when it came to controlling that engine down there, most of the world didn't speak digital.
所以如果我想给作动器发指令 它们可不懂数字语言
So if I want to talk to those actuators they ain't in the digital world.
所以这项工作是交给模拟计算机完成的
So that was done with the analog computer.
而我们通过控制发动机摆动来控制火箭飞行方向这方面
And this business of where we're controlling the rocket by moving the engines.
还记得我们要控制火箭的弯曲模态吗
Well, remember, we're creating these bending modes and we want to control that.
我们要防止火箭飞行时自己把自己掰断
We don't want to break in two,
所以火箭上还有一组速率陀螺仪 数据输入给模拟计算机
so they actually have another set of rate gyroscopes that feed into the analog computer
从而计算在特定时间点 我最多能摆动发动机多少度
that it then uses to determine how much I can actually can move this engine at any particular point in time.
计算机会不停发送指令 我现在在这 你发动机只能摆动这么多
The computer's sending commands over to say, okay, I'm in this time base. You can move it this much.
我现在在那 你现在只能摆动那么多
I'm in this time, you can move it this much.
两者之间是有数据交互的
So they're talking to each other,
但最终发送指令摆动发动机的是模拟计算机的工作
but the analog computer ultimately sends the command down to move the engine.
有意思 所以有一个数字模拟转换的过程
Interesting. So there's a D to A.
是模拟与数字系统的合作
and then... It's a combination of analog and digital.
所以您在当中搭建了一座桥梁
So you were bridging a gap.
呃 主要是因为……当时条件如此
Yeah, well, that was that was that was what we had at the time.
后来 航天飞机出来以后
Now once shuttle came along, remember, now
航天飞机有计算机连接各种东西的
shuttle has the computers and then everything is datalink down to whatever.
所以假如你想移动副翼 比如在再入大气的时候
So if you want to move the ailerons, let's say you're reentering, you want to move the ailerons.
数字信号会直接下发到那边 那边有一个转换器
Well, you send that digital signal down and then there's a converter down here
可以进行转换 变成模拟信号
that will actually convert it to whatever the analog is to
从而控制 比如某某作动器之类的 大致如此
move the whatever kind of actuator, you know, and so forth.
所以纵观历史 你会发现数字计算机在控制流程中越走越远
So as you go forward, you see that the digital is moving farther and farther down the line.
所以您觉得自己是一位先驱吗?
So did you feel like a pioneer?
我只是觉得自己是一个不知道到底发生了什么的人
I just felt like somebody who didn't know what the heck was going on.
我是在1965年大学毕业的
I got out, I finished college in 1965 Okay?
我当时完全没有上过任何计算机的课程 完全不懂数字内容
I had had zero computer courses of any kind, no digital anything.
学的一切都是模拟的
It was all analog.
实际上我当时学的东西都是大功率的那些玩意
In fact, all my stuff was high was like TVA power, you know, high big power stuff.
所以我到这以后完全就是从零开始学习
So I came here and had to learn a whole 'nother world.
但这一点在我看来是有点……
But this is a point that in my mind
可悲吧 因为它没有得到更多的宣传
is kind of sad that it hasn't been promoted more.
项目最忙的时候 有30万家承包商 4万7千名NASA员工在做这件事
When this program was at its peak, there were 300,000 contractors
and 47,000 NASA employees working on this thing.
很多承包商都是像我们一样来自大学
Well a lot of us contractors had come from college and we had come into this,
参与项目的有相当多的年轻人
a lot of young folks working on these programs.
我们在这项目上学到了东西后 就调走了
The things that we learned in this then we moved,
你懂吧 就是各种项目结束后
you know, after these programs phased down,
我们很多人都去了其他的领域
most of us went off to other... other fields.
所以我最开始是做这个项目 负责飞行评估等等
So I started with this and doing flight evaluation and so forth and,
知道吧 系统和组件问题 尝试解决发生的事情
you know, systems and component issues, trying to work through what happened.
然后这个项目结束了
Then this all ended.
我们去开发天空实验室的计算机与控制系统
We did the computer and the control system for Skylab, worked on that.
我们在亨茨维尔这里的设施给休斯顿提供7x24小时的任务支持
We had a 24 hour, seven day a week mission support
tied in with Houston from our facility here in Huntsville.
之后土星五号的任务就都结束了
And then this all really phased down.
NASA预算缩减 当时还不清楚航天飞机未来如何
NASA was getting budget cuts and not really sure where to go with shuttle.
所以我们很多人都转行了
So a lot of us went to other things.
我在爱国者导弹项目上干了几年 然后IBM这边关门了
I worked on a Patriot missile program for several years and then IBM closed here.
我们去了北卡罗来纳州的IBM商业部
We went to North Carolina in the commercial side of IBM,
继续把我所知道的 我在这里学到的很多东西应用在工作中
applying what I know, a lot of what I learned here.
然后IBM需要一些了解计算机科学的工程师
Then they decided, well, we need some engineers that can know some computer science
所以他们把我们送回去 拿计算机科学学位
so they sent us back, get a computer science degree.
因此 我在IBM的最后一份工作是编写软件来读取个人支票上的手写金额
So my last job at IBM was I was writing software to read handwritten amounts off of personal checks.
真假?
Really?
可能是有史以来第一次让机器学习广泛应用于商业
That was the first, probably one of the first widespread
commercial applications of machine learning that was ever done.
老牛逼了
That was terrific. Fun job.
-所以您从最初 这台计算机上的第一个晶体管开始……  -没错
So you went from, you went from some of the first transistors ever... Right.
-一路走到了机器学习  -是的
To machine learning. Yeah.
-这就是您的职业生涯  -是的
In your career. Yeah.
什么感觉?
What's that like?
挺牛的吧
That's pretty neat.
在IBM工作31年后 我从IBM退休
And then I retired from IBM after 31 years,
搬回亨茨维尔 又在爱国者导弹上工作了19年时间
moved back to Huntsville, and spent another 19 years working on Patriot again.
-哇  -这就是我的51年职业生涯
Wow. I had a 51 year career.
-太牛了  -是吧
That's amazing. Yeah.
-而您现在仍投身科普教育工作  -乐在其中~
And you're still and you're still educating, right now? It's still fun.
您太牛了 Luke
That's amazing, Luke.
您还想讲些什么呢?
So where do you wanna go from here?
继续到顶部讲讲? 还是……
Should we go to the pointy end? Or go ahead.
呃……这样吧!
That's... all right.
刚讲的内容 我再多提一件事情
Let's talk about one more thing here where we talked about
当船箭分离 开始奔月的时候
when the crew separated, went on their way.
我们让三级火箭减速 瞄准撞月或者飞离月球进入绕日轨道
Then we target, we slowed this stage down and targeted the moon and tried to throw it in orbit.
而阿波罗12号 那次任务
Let's go to Apollo 12.
绝对是 各种工程师心中最梦幻的一发
Apollo 12 was absolutely one of the, an engineer's dream.
它发生了什么玄幻故事 你都想象不到
There were more crazy things happened on that one than you can imagine
它上面的仪器舱 装有C波段转发器
With this one, there's, the instrument unit has a C-band transponder.
就是 C波段 5GHz的转发器
All right, C-Band 5,000 megahertz transmitter.
很精准
Very accurate.
地面的任务控制中心的人 使用C波段追踪数据
So the ground, the mission control folks, they use the C-band transponder tracking data,
和箭上计算的数据进行对比
compare that with the onboard computed data,
可以给箭上发指令 告诉你比如x轴上偏离了多少多少
and say, well, you, you're a little bit off in the x axis so they can send up a command and say,
然后让你进行一个小小的修正之类的操作
well, you need to make this little correction in the <unknown> to do whatever.
3200公里
我们当时想让它从2000英里高度 月球轨迹后部飞掠月球进入绕日轨道
So what we're trying to do is we're trying to send this thing 2,000 miles
past the trailing edge to get thrown into solar orbit.
在阿波罗12号上 地面追踪系统觉得它……
On Apollo 12, the tracking system was such that they thought they were going
比实际中要快一点
faster than they actually were,
40km/h 11.2m/s
所以给它发送了一个额外25英里每小时的减速指令
so they slowed it down another 25 miles an hour beyond what was already programed.
结果我们错过了月球 偏了几千英里
Well, turns out we missed the moon... several thousand miles.
最后它进入了一个非常非常高的绕地轨道
It goes into very, very high orbit about the earth,
1.13万x80万 公里
我记得大约是70000x50000英里吧
something like a 70,000 mile by maybe 500,000 miles something.
是个非常非常高的轨道
It's it's really very high orbit.
在之后几年
Over the next several years,
随着它在这样的轨道上运行
this thing apparently, as it's going in this orbit,
会同时受到地球和月球的引力影响
is getting affected by the earth's gravity and the moon's gravity.
轨道也在慢慢变形
So the orbit slowly gets stretched.
然后 航天里有一个词叫第一拉格朗日点
Well, there's a point called Lagrange L1 point
在那里 月球 不是 太阳和地球的引力会平衡
where the gravity of the moon, I mean, the gravity of the sun and the gravity of the earth equal.
地球和太阳一起往两侧施加引力
Earth's pulling this way the same amount as the sun's pulling that way.
然后 我估计应该是JPL的那帮人
Well, the people at I believe it's JPL,
他们计算后发现这东西的轨道会慢慢挪到途径L1点
they, they believe that this thing's orbit stretched out to the point
然后等它飞过L1点后 最终会进入一个绕日轨道
that it went beyond the L1 point and was ultimately pulled into orbit around the sun after all.
所以它最终的确还是进入了绕日轨道
So this thing goes out there and he orbits the sun.
当然了 我们好多人都说"哎呀我早说它要进绕日轨道的吧~"
Of course, everybody said, oh, well, we knew that would happen. Yeah right.
"有谁相信吗?"
Anybody believe that?
大约30年后 在2002年
About 30 years later, 2002
一位业余天文爱好者 想不起来叫什么了
杨光宇 生于香港 业余天文学家
他发现了大量的小行星 并为之命名
比如(26738) Lishizhen 李时珍 (28980) Chowyunfat 周润发
(42295) Teresateng 邓丽君 (55381) Lautakwah 刘德华
(110288) Libai 李白 (110289) Dufu 杜甫
amateur astronomer who I cannot remember his name.
他有一堆自己命名的小行星 他就专门找这个的
He has got his name on a lot of asteroids because he's an asteroid hunter.
他观测到了一个白点
Sees this white dot.
然后他上网 申报这个东西 他可能觉得这是个新的小行星吧
Goes on the Internet, reports that he thinks this is an asteroid, whatever.
JPL和 可能是MIT的人吧 观测之后感觉不对劲
JPL and I think MIT people start looking at it and they're scratching their heads.
"不对 这玩意轨迹肯定不是小行星"
Naw, the trajectory can't be an asteroid.
然后 我觉得应该是JPL的Paul Chodas博士
Dr. Paul Chodas
小行星动力学和撞击概率方面的权威
JPL近地天体项目办公室(JPL NEO Program Office)
使用的轨道定位与星历软件的总设计师
哨兵撞击监测系统开发者之一
And I believe it's this Dr. Paul Chodas at JPL,
他的团队会追踪太空垃圾 然后他们开始观测这个物体
their group started looking at it and they are the people who track space junk.
他说他进行了一些反向的计算
And he said that he had done some back figuring
觉得它是阿波罗12号火箭的三级
and thought this was actually the third stage from Apollo 12,
它又重新进入地球轨道了
and it was coming back into orbit around the Earth.
-在2002年?  -是的  -哇
In 2002. 2002. Wow.
拉格朗日点的位置是跟随地球绕日公转而移动的
So this Lagrange point follows the earth around the sun.
而它进入了某种绕日轨道
This thing had gotten into some orbit about the sun,
可能是离地球挺近的一个还算稳定的轨道上
and this just, you know, I mean it's going to stay in that same pretty well orbit.
可能有点进动 但大体上还算稳定
It may precess a little bit, but for the most part.
而拉格朗日点的位置是跟随地球走的
So this Lagrange point now is following the Earth,
而在某个时刻 三级火箭 地球 拉格朗日点 刚好处在正确的位置上
well, at this point in time, S-IVB, the Earth and the Lagrange point just happened to be at the right point.
导致它就……
And this thing gets
三级火箭和仪器舱 刚好被地球拽回了绕地轨道
S-IVB and the instrument unit get pulled back into orbit around the earth
之后它在绕地轨道运行了大约一年 在某一圈中又接近了月球
so it orbits the earth for about a year, gets near the moon on one of these orbits
并再次被月球甩进了绕日轨道
and gets thrown back into solar orbit again.
JPL的人认为它未来还会回来
Now, the people at JPL said they think this is going to happen again.
大约每40年发生一次
It will re-happen about every 40 years
在未来一两千年内反复 直到某次撞上地球或月球
for the next 1,000 or 2,000, ultimately it'll run into the earth or the moon.
而这一切都是因为那个小小的黑色装置
And that's all because this little module right here,
三级尾部的APS 点火了
the APS on the back of the third stage fired
40km/h 11.2m/s
-多给了仅仅25英里每小时的速度增量  -没错
just a little bit... 25 miles per hour too much. Yeah.
导致这个三级火箭进入了……
And that put this thing in...
导致了后续一堆幺蛾子 对
That started all this foolishness. Right.
哈哈哈哈一堆幺蛾子笑死我
So.. It started all this foolishness!
对 没错
Yeah, right.
所以它现在还在太空飘着
So this guy is still floating around.
如果你想了解它 可以上网搜索 "J002E3"
If you want to know about it, you can go out on the internet and do an internet search on J002E3.
是它的物体编号
That's the space junk number for this thing.
还能搜到JPL给它做的轨迹图 相对于地球 月球和L1点的
And there is a there a couple of people have put plots of
what the JPL simulation is that shows this thing coming around L1 orbiting the Earth.
可以发现它每圈的轨道会有怎样的变化
And you can see every time it gets close to Earth, you can see how the shape of the orbit changes.
还能看到它最后一圈遇到月球的时候是怎样
And then on this last one, it comes around and the moon just
biu的一下被甩出地球轨道的
(toomp) grabs it and throws it out into orbit.
但 但我的孙子未来还能看到它
But but my grandkids will see it again.
-没错  -牛逼 太有意思了
Good. That's amazing. That's awesome.
你想想两千年后一个倒霉蛋正在街上走呢
Some poor slob 2,000 years from now going to be walking down the street,
发现ta的影子突然变大
seeing his shadow getting big real big, real quick.
咣叽一下 中大奖了
Oh, smack. Wonder what that was?
笑死我了
That's amazing.
Luke 您跟我们讲了好多火箭方面的 它的三级 它的仪器舱
All right, Luke, you've talked a lot about the rocket, all three stages, the instrumentation ring here.
然后我们还讲了它顶端的逃逸塔
And then we get up to this this business up here.
我发现您很少提及中间的飞船部分
I notice you don't talk a lot about this side over here.
嗯 是 毕竟我是搞火箭的嘛
Well, yeah. Well, we were the rocket guys.
我负责那部分
We, you know, that was our part.
-您就像火车头一样  -哈哈哈对
You were like a tractor. Yeah.
-您把他们拉到了地方  -没错
You hauled them up there. That's right. And then, and then,
所以剩余飞船部分是归林顿·约翰逊航天中心负责的
so Johnson would handle most of this.
对 从仪器舱开始往上的部分都是归林顿·约翰逊航天中心负责的
Yeah, well, the Johnson Space... from the instrument unit forward is all Johnson Space Center.
这些都归他们管
They're responsible for all of that.
那您的工作从火箭点火 T0开始 到大约什么时候结束?
So your job was done in how much time? Once you know, from T0 to how, well..?
设备舱上面的电池可以维持11-12小时
Well the instrument unit would last about 11 to 12 hours. The batteries would run down.
等电耗光 就没别的能做的了
So after that, we couldn't do anything else.
我就负责这块了
You know, that was that was our part.
给人送到奔月轨道 三级部分要么绕日要么撞月 二选一
We got them on their way and we got this thing heading either
in solar orbit, or we're going crashing into the moon, one of the two.
就这样 而且每次发射都很顺利
And then that that was, you know, the launch vehicle's pretty well done all they can do.
那您能讲讲发射那天是怎样的流程吗?
So. So can you just walk me through up to launch day?
那种感觉如何? 您和您庞大的团队做出这样的成果后
What did it feel like? You did all this work, you and a huge team?
肯定不只您一人吧
Not just you, obviously.
那肯定 老多人了
Oh yeah, lots of folks. Yeah. Yeah.
所以 发射那天内心感受如何?
What, what did it feel like on launch day?
到什么时间点 您的心才算彻底放下? 或者会放下吗?
Did, and at what point did you feel relief? Or did you?
不会彻底放下吧 因为我们之后还得回去……
Not really, because we would actually go back
我们团队会在发射前36小时开始干活
our group would start about 36 hours before the launch.
我们在IBM的设施那边有个办公室
We had a room over here at our IBM facility.
还有几个人在亨茨维尔运营支援中心 HOSC
We had a couple of people that were out at the, the HOSC they call it Huntsville Operations Support Center.
然后我们还有些人 应该就一个吧 在卡角待命
And then we had some folks that were, one guy who was at the Cape.
所以 从发射前大约36小时开始
And so starting 36 hours before launch,
我们绝大多数工程师会待在IBM这边
we would have most of our engineers were over here at the IBM site.
几个在HOSC那里 前几次发射是这样安排的
We had a couple out at HOSC and this was the first couple of missions, okay.
再后来 我们有了更多的人留在这边的马歇尔太空飞行中心
After that we had more people out at the center out here at Marshall, and
应该是从……第四次发射开始吧
starting with the fourth flight,
我当时负责HOSC的一个控制台
I was actually working on one of the consoles at HOSC.
那天有个同事生重病了 来不了
We had one of our people who had become critically ill and couldn't do it.
是别的部门的人
So it was a different department.
但上面说了 发射前那边必须得有人看着
But they said, Well, you guys need to be there for the pre launch.
那就由你去负责其中一个控制台吧
So sitting there operating one of the consoles is as good a place as any.
然后我就去了HOSC
So I started doing that then.
我们当时 差不多是干12小时休12小时
So we would be about, we would do like 12 hours on, 12 hours off,
从发射前36小时开始 直到发射全程
starting about 36 hours before, going through the launch,
前后加起来得有48小时吧
which is about a 48 hour period total.
当火箭发射后
Once the thing is launched,
我们负责的仪器舱
then the instrument unit, our part of it,
仪器舱上的电池能维持11到12个小时的时间
the instrument unit would last about 11 to 12 hours until the batteries would run down
等电池耗光就算完活了
and that would be it because we couldn't do anything.
就这样了
We... wasn't anything else.
电池耗光那一刻 您有没有一种"成了!"的感觉?
Once the batteries were exhausted, did you have a feeling of We did it!?
呃 当然 感觉肯定非常好
Well, yeah, always felt good.
我要说的是 第二天早上
The thing was, is the next morning
我们会去HOSC那边 做一次快速分析
we would do what was called a quick look analysis and we would go out to the HOSC.
在今天可能理所当然 有各种花哨的可视化数据表格 可当时没有
Now, this is before all the fancy days of plots and stuff
that we have today and we all take for granted.
马歇尔中心的计算机实验室能给我们做出一堆数据图表
Marshall's Center Comp Lab, they had the ability to make a series of plots for us.
于是各个分级的所有承包商
So all the all the contractors from the stages,
一级二级三级的全来了
you know, the first stage, second, third,
负责那些的公司 还有制造发动机的人
the companies from those, the people that build the engines.
这些人 加上我们负责仪器舱的人 全都会去HOSC
You know, all these people plus us from the IU, we would go out to the HOSC
乌泱泱的人群会占据整个计算机实验室和走廊
and they would have the hallways and the comp lab,
拿图钉把各自的数据图表挂得到处都是
they've got stuff thumbtacked to the wall all over the place, with these little plots.
我们到那 拿上我们负责的部分
So we would go out and for whatever part I'm responsible for,
我是从图表里做好记录 都写下来
I go out and I take notes from that plot and write them all down, you know,
然后当天下午回去处理 做一个报告出来
and then go back to work that, that afternoon and put together a presentation
用于第二天早上做一个"正式速查"
to give the next morning, which we call the formal quick look
届时所有NASA的人和承包商都会到马歇尔中心一个大会议室里
where we got all the NASA folks and the contractors in a big conference room out there at Marshall
我们会报告哪些部分正常工作了 哪些部分没有
and we give our presentation for what worked, what didn't work,
没工作的部分打算要怎么解决 你懂吧
what we're going to do to try to resolve what didn't work, you know.
所以已经开始为下次发射做准备了
So so you're looking forward to the next launch already.
呃 完整分析所有数据还要大约两个月的时间
Well, we're, we will it will take about two months for us to finally analyze all the data.
等第三个月出一个最终报告
And then we would do about a three month final report
就可以为下次发射做准备了
and then we would get ready for the next one.
您回过头看过自己当年的报告吗?
Have you ever gone back and look and looked at your old reports?
看过 看过……
Yeah. Yeah. And
有些……和今天也没啥区别嘛
some... shouldn't say that different.
-和今天吗?  -对
Even today. Yeah.
有意思
That's amazing.
尤其和今天比是吧
Especially today.
现在网上有好多资料的
You know, there's a lot of that stuff that's out there on the internet.
你可以直接查到阿波罗12号的飞行评估报告
https://history.nasa.gov/afj/ap12fj/pdf/a12-saturn-v-fer.pdf
You can go out and look for the flight evaluation report for Apollo 12
或者查发射编号 "AS-5XX" AS代表"阿波罗/土星"
or AS Apollo Saturn, Dash 501.
501就是土星五号第一次发射 之后是502 503 以此类推
That would be the first Saturn V launch and then 501, two, three, four, five, so on.
您写了哪个部分?
What parts did you write?
呃 我写了……这个得看情况
Uh, I did, well, it depended.
干的活一直在变 我写过电子系统 遥测系统
You know, you changed through. The electrical system, telemetry system,
还有ECS 环境控制系统
and ECS, environmental control.
我主要会写这些部分
Those were my primary ones.
后来 做制导部分的一个人 做制导平台的
And then later on, the guy that was doing one of the, part of the guidance, the guidance platform,
他调走了 他的活就交给其他人干了
he had gone somewhere, transferred to somewhere else.
所以我接手了其中一部分工作
So I picked up that part of it.
那段时间我们都是混着来的 各种杂活都干
And then over time, we all just kind of scrambled around and did pieces here and there.
当时有一个挺大的 必须要在电脑上做的分析
We had one big analysis we had to do on the computer where
一开始还不确定当时一切是否能正常工作
we were not real sure things were doing what they were supposed to do.
但完成的时候
But once we got done
是我第一次真正接触到计算机的细枝末节 了解它们是如何工作的
and that was my first real exposure to the nitty gritty of the computers, how they worked.
我还想问您
Let me ask you this.
这枚火箭上从头到尾有无数的零件
So there's literally tons of components all the way up to, you know, from tip all the way to tail.
-无数人参与其中 您刚说大约35万人?  -嗯
A lot of people. You said 350,000 or so. Yeah.
-当时的工作氛围怎么样?  -非常好
What was the atmosphere like in terms of teamwork? Great.
是人们各干各的吗?
Did people have their own thing?
比如 我是这方面专家 我在做这个 你也不用管我 还是说
Like, I'm working on this and I'm the expert and you don't get near my stuff, or was.
是怎样的一种氛围?
What was it like?
那可能是我这辈子经历的最棒的工作环境
It, that was probably the best environment I ever worked in.
并不是你想的那样
It was not that way.
每个人都在互相帮助
Everybody helped everybody.
成堆的文件
There were documents.
每套系统 各个部件都有一堆文件
Each system, we had a series of documents on the components.
还有负责整套系统总体的文件 比如……
We had a serie... and a document on the entire system, like in like the
电力系统
power system, electric power,
遥测系统
the telemetry system.
转发器 复用器 信号调节器 各种文件
We had, we had documents written on the transmitter, on the multiplexers, on the signal conditioning.
你懂吧 一堆东西
You know, all that stuff was
你要什么信息 马上就能给你找
if you needed information, you could get it.
获取非常方便
It was readily available.
可能是我这辈子经历的最棒的工作环境
That was that was probably the best working environment I was ever in.
-真的?  -嗯
Really? Yep.
当您看到尼尔·阿姆斯特朗走出登月舱的时候 是什么感觉?
So what did it feel like when you saw Neil Armstrong step out of the out of the spacecraft?
呃 挺酷吧
You know, pretty cool.
我觉得最大的问题是我女儿当时挡着电视呢
I think the biggest problem was my daughter was sitting in front of the TV
-我压根没看到  -真的?
and I couldn't see. Really?
"宝啊 挪一挪让你爹看眼电视行不行"
Carmen, move over a little bit.
就是这样 我感觉我们都……
And that was, I think we all
有点……
kind of
内心"哇"的感觉吧 难以置信
just WOW! Can't believe this.
而您也参与其中
And you were a part of it.
嗯 是的 做了点微小的贡献
Oh, yeah. Yeah. Had a little bit, a little piece of it.
太牛了
That's amazing.
-可不是小贡献呀  -反正挺有意思的
That's a big deal. It was a lot of fun.
嗯 我觉得很多……
Yeah. I think a lot of the
真要总结下来的话 我觉得最大的……
if you try to summarize the whole thing, I think the biggest,
当然了 整体是很棒的
you know, all this was good.
但我觉得他们做的最不好的一点是……
And I think one of, the big mistakes that were... has been
他们对从这个项目中收获到什么 宣发得不够
made was that it was not put forward enough
to tell the public what they got back from this.
就好像我刚说 我曾经搞过机器学习
I mean, you know, like I'm telling you, I'm out here working with machine learning
其中的很多问题我们都在六七十年代的计算机上遇到过
and a lot of that had to do with this first problem we had with that computer,
怎么回事大家都琢磨过 懂吧
trying to understand what was going on, you know.
最后我去了北卡罗来纳州 到那第一年教微处理器
Ultimately, I went to North Carolina, and first year there I was teaching microprocessors.
我当时的邻居在英特尔工作
I had a neighbor that worked for Intel,
他给了我一堆教学资料 我先自学 学会了就出去教书
and he got me all kinds of educational materials that I taught myself and went out and taught classes.
仅仅一年我们就顺利转行到别的领域了
And that for a year that we were starting a new site.
-所以您的意思是 阿波罗工程给纳税人带来的回报远超投资?  -没错没错
So. So you're saying the taxpayer got a huge return on investment? Oh, yes. Oh yes.
如此庞大的研发项目
These big research and development programs,
你很难想象后面会给我们带来多大财富
it's just incredible what you get out of it.
记得之前说的 一级火箭材料的焊接吗
You know, we're talking about welding on that first stage.
可能外面跑的每辆车都有那个技术的影子
Probably every automobile out there has got that technology in it,
懂吧 所以……
you know, and so...
您期待未来新的登月工程吗?
Are you excited about the the new lunar program?
当然
Yeah. Yeah.
我真的……
I really
希望能顺利吧 我……
hope it all works. I...
我心中长远目标是登上火星
my problem is the long term goal is go to Mars.
但登上火星这样的工程 需要建立一个长达25年的计划
To go to Mars, we're going to have to set a 25 year plan.
而我们这个国家 并不擅长这个时间尺度的规划
Our country is not good at 25 year plans.
有时候一年甚至几个月的事都弄不明白
We have a hard time getting a year or three months sometimes.
如果真要去火星 就得做好规划 并坚持下去
And if we're going to go to Mars, we're going to have to set a plan and stick to it.
从上到下 各层的决策者都要坚持下去
From administration to administration, we're going to have to stick to it.
不然肯定没戏
Otherwise, it'll never happen.
-您打算怎样做?  -那我就不知道了
How would you do this? That's... I don't know.
这时候就得看那些说客的真本事了
But that that's going to take some real salesmanship from somebody.
我不清楚谁有能力完成 NASA 还是民营航天 还是中国航天
And I don't know whether NASA or private industry or China or somebody else will do it.
送人往返火星 全程要花三年的时间
Person going on a Mars mission's going to be gone three years.
想要坚持这三年
And to, to make it three years...
接下来是我的个人观点
Now this is my personal opinion.
说了可能这些航天中心的人听了要皱眉
These people here, Rocket Center, probably wouldn't like it.
我今天站在这说 去火星要有长达25年的规划
But as I stand here today and say it's going to take me 25 years to finally get to Mars.
站在当下 回看过去25年 想想当时的科技水平
I think where we are now and go back 25, look at technology,
从那时看未来的种种可能 你会很迷茫
look at possibility going forward, you begin to wonder,
"人类真能当上火星吗?"
would it make sense to send people to Mars?
"每个人都要带25吨的东西 吃的 喝的 擦屁股的全算上"
For every person you send, you've got to take 25 tons of stuff food, water, toilet paper, all this stuff.
"但要是送机器人的话 25吨"
Send a robot, 25 tons.
"25吨我能送一大帮机器人了 而且只晒太阳就能干活"
I can send a lot of robots for 25 tons and they only eat sunshine.
所以给未来做决策 是一件非常非常困难的事情
So going forward, that's going to be a lot of tough, tough decisions.
假如你想送人上去 想看到人类做到这件事
You want to, you want to send people, you want to see people do it.
我的意思是就 人性使然
I mean, that's just human nature.
但你要问我能不能做到? 我也不知道
But will it happen? I don't know.
那您觉得我们能从去火星这样的计划中收获到什么?
What do you think we will gain out of that? You...
都一个意思啦
Well, it's it's the same thing.
到时候技术肯定会……
Your, your technology's going to
肯定会有新技术产生 我们也肯定会获益于此
you know, it's going to be there and you're going to be building off of it.
真让我指出来哪里会获益很难 但……
Yeah. Hard to put your finger on one thing, but...
所以在您的生涯中 您从仪器舱上第一个晶体管 到最后研究机器学习
So you went from, in your career, you went from transistors on this thing,
some of the first transistors to machine learning.
您认为下一代的电气工程师身上会发生什么?
What do you think is going to happen in the next generation of electrical engineers?
我就说嘛 所以我说往未来看的话
That's why I say, you know, that's why I say going forward,
你上网看那些……
if you go on the internet and you look at
比如波士顿动力 他们家的机器人
Boston Dynamics robots and you look at the robots
再看看我们现在有什么 你心里就会想
and you look at what we have today and then you just think,
"天啊 这要是25年之后会是啥样"
man, where are we going to be 25 years from now?
或者十年之后 懂吧
Or ten years or, you know,
然后就会很迷茫 我们未来何去何从
and you really have to wonder, what what in the world are we going to do?
我说不出 我……
I don't know. I just
我真的不知道
I have no idea.
总之就是 从现在到那时 会有很多令人困惑事情
But I just tell you, there's there's a lot a lot of head scratching between now and then.
有意思
That's amazing.
谢谢您抽空和我聊这些 受益匪浅
That's all. Well, Luke, thank you for your time. I really appreciate it. Ok, all righty.
-这个  -您想聊聊它吗?
Well, this. You want to walk over there?
这是阿波罗16号的指令舱
This is the Apollo spacecraft from Apollo 16.
如果看它的背面 你会发现
If you look on the back of it, you see that it's
整个底部都覆盖一种
the whole thing is covered with a
一种材料
material,
烧蚀材料 因为它再入大气的时候会经历……你懂的
ablative material so that as you reenter and this thing gets up to, you know,
2000摄氏度左右
三四千华氏度 又不能给它熔化了
3,000, 4,000 degrees, you don't melt everything.
这一面看上去还不错
Well, this part of it looks pretty good.
但你绕到后面看到迎风面 就能看到烧得有多狠了
But then you see where it's actually hitting the atmosphere, you can see where it's charred.
它这现在已经面目全非了 因为经过了一些处理
Now, this thing is all beat up because of handling and whatever.
人们会从上面取样
And people probably were taking pieces of it off for samples.
你能看到上面还有打孔
And then you see the holes that have been drilled in them.
那是人们为了分析结构 观察材料表现用的
Those are to analyze the structure and see how well it behaved.
这东西 回到地球的时候 真的非常非常热
So this thing coming down, it gets pretty doggone hot.
然后如果往里看
Now, as you look inside,
感觉好像空间不是很大
you see that it doesn't look like there's much room.
但这些座椅其实可以向后折叠
But now these couches actually fold back out of
能平放到抵着底部的位置 这样能多出来点空间
sort of back up against the wall here so that there's a little more room
所以可能没想象中那么挤
to move around down in there than you might think.
但当然了 对于三个人来说空间仍然不大
But for three people, there's not a whole lot of room.
十天任务结束 仨人之间啥秘密都没有了
After a ten day mission there ain't no secrets.
哈哈哈哈 都看光了
Ain't no secrets, that's pretty good.
-我看后面还有块月球岩石?  -对
And there's a moon rock on the backside, right? Yep.
您认识施密特博士吗?
哈里森·施密特 美国地质学家
阿波罗17号登月舱驾驶员
唯一一位登上月球的科学家
微信开屏画面就是他拍的
Which one, now you know, Dr. Schmitt, right?
见过而已 不算认识
Well, I met him, but I don't know him.
这块来自阿波罗12号
So this one's Apollo 12.
-12号?  -嗯
This is Apollo 12. Yeah.
看到这样一块来自月球的岩石
What's it like to see a rock from the moon
而它还有您的团队一份功劳 是什么感受
that your team helped helped gather?
挺震撼的
Pretty amazing.
阿波罗12号指令长
那是皮特·康拉德拿着一小块的照片
And Pete Conrad holding some of them over there.
他是阿波罗12号成员
He was on 12.
阿波罗12号任务挺有意思的
Apollo 12 was an interesting flight.
起飞的时候被闪电击中了
av11069492
Struck by lightning and
阿波罗12号登月舱驾驶员
艾伦·宾在他们溅落大西洋的时候
Alan Bean, when they popped into the Atlantic,
有个相机固定在他头顶一个支架上
the camera was mounted in a bracket up above his head.
溅落的时候掉下来 给他脑袋砸挂彩了
指令舱溅落时遇到升起的海浪 导致相机从支架上脱落
砸中他的头 造成轻微脑震荡 缝了六针
It fell down and split his head open and slight concussion.
所以说12号真的挺有意思的 还有相机 登月的相机还被太阳烧了
So 12 was an interesting flight and the camera, the TV camera got hosed on,
他们刚把相机拿出来 就不小心对着太阳了 结果啥视频都没录下来
as soon as they tried to take it out, and set it up so they didn't have any video from it.
-真的?  -嗯
Really? Yeah.
您每次发射这些小事都记得吗?
So do you remember each flight?
零零散散吧
Bits and pieces of them. Yeah. Yeah.
牛
That's wild.
-那边那个东西才有意思呢  -那是天空实验室吗?
That thing over there, that's interesting. That's Skylab.
-对  -那是掉到澳大利亚的碎片吗?
Yeah. That... That's the piece that fell on Esperance. Right?
对 它最后掉到澳大利亚了
Yeah. That thing wound up in Australia and uh
我爷爷之前在天空实验室项目工作过 他在马歇尔太空飞行中心
My grandfather worked on Skylab. Yeah. He was at Marshall.
是吗? 叫什么名字?
Oh, yeah. Who, what was his name?
Wilson "Fess" Sandlin
Wilson "Fess" Sandlin 1928-1999 NASA制图工程师
Uh, Wilson Sandlin, as Fess.
-啊 不清楚这位  -他是制图的
He, uh. I didn't know him. Yeah, he was a drafter.
他应该不是负责火箭的 他负责过天空实验室上的"浴室"
He didn't work on the actual rocket, I don't believe. Yeah, he did work on the shower for Skylab.
啊 我明白了
Yeah. Oh, yeah.
我还记得当时想研究我爷爷设计的"浴室"
I remember trying to do some research on the shower that Granddaddy helped design,
想着应该会很厉害
thinking it was going to be amazing.
结果各种报告显示 宇航员们的洗澡体验非常糟糕
And all the reports I read, the astronauts said the shower was awful.
对 他们只能用擦的 没法洗淋浴
Yeah. They use, they use wipes now they never, don't use shower.
对
Yeah.
-水珠会飘得到处都是  -没错
Those droplets just go everywhere. They do.
我当时做爱国者项目的时候 应该是1977年吧
We were here working on Patriot, would've been 77, I guess.
NASA的人给我打电话 问我知道怎么给天空实验室重新"开机"吗
We got a call from the NASA guys and asked if we remembered how to power up Skylab.
然后我和一个叫汤姆的 他负责软件 我负责硬件
So two of us, one guy Tom was the software guy and I was the hardware guy.
我俩当晚回家 在车库里翻出一堆文件
So we went home that night and to our archives in our garages
弄出一套给那玩意重启的程序
and came up with a procedure to power that thing back up.
当时的情况是 地球……呃 太阳的周期活动
And what had happened was the earth, uh, I mean, the sun periodically
会有一系列的太阳耀斑活动 会产生紫外线
goes through a series of solar flares, and they produce ultraviolet light.
紫外线会导致地球上层大气向外膨胀
Ultraviolet light causes the upper atmosphere to expand.
我左手是地球
This is the earth.
天空实验室留轨姿态是这样垂直地面的 我们叫重力梯度姿态
We had left Skylab in an attitude like, this which is called a gravity gradient attitude.
它环绕地球的时候 一直保持这样竖着的姿态
So as it goes around the earth, it stays in that position.
微重力环境下 上下重力差产生的重力梯度力矩可以让航天器保持稳定
Gravity difference here versus there in a microgravity environment makes this a stable orbit.
而当它迎风撞上膨胀的大气 就会开始震动
Well, this big bulge in the atmosphere, come around hit it broadside, it starts shaking around.
所以搞软件的汤姆想到一个方案
So Tom software guy comes up with a scheme
给天空实验室调整姿态 让它像这样水平飞
where they reorient Skylab so that it goes around like so.
但这样我们就得一直控制它 而之前重力梯度姿态时上面设备都关了
Now we're having to control it all the time now. Before in this attitude, everything's powered off.
现在改成平飞 就得一直进行控制 让小头端做迎风面
So now we're like so. We're having to control it so that the the small end hits that bulge.
大概正常运行了一年吧 后来赶上一系列太阳耀斑的活动
For about a year it did fine, but then the sun went through a whole series of flares
整个地球的大气都开始膨胀了
and the whole atmosphere around the entire Earth expanded.
从那之后 整个航天器阻力明显变大 最后直接就掉下来了
And at that, after that, we were in the atmosphere all the time, and that's what brought it down.
-真的?  -嗯
Really? Yeah.
-所以你们当时是控制天空实验室上的动量轮?  -对
So you guys were controlling the control moment gyros on Skylab or..? Yeah.
-牛啊 是您控制的  -对
That's amazing, you could point it. Yeah. That's amazing.
我们之前提过箱间段吧
We were talking about that intertank.
-嗯  -储箱共底部分
Yeah. The bulkhead.
这就是共底储箱中间的……
This is what's between those tanks on the...
-哇 好厚啊  -确实
Oh, wow. That's pretty big. Yeah.
-它就是隔热的吗?  它就是共底的部分
So that's the insulator. That's the bulkhead between the...
-液氢和液氧之间?  -对
The oxygen and hydrogen? Yeah. Wow. Yeah.
好牛 哇看这个
That's amazing. Look at this.
-这就是他们处理……相连的部分  -对
So this is how they handled that.. Yeah. Interface. Yup.
-所以在一级上 有两个分开的储箱  -对
Okay, so on the first stage, you had two tanks. Yep.
因为两个箱体是分开的 所以中间要浪费这么多空间
And because you had two different sections, you had all this wasted space in between?
-还有重量  -还有重量
And weight. And weight.
-所以共底储箱应运而生 解决了这个问题  -没错
Okay, so when you have that common bulkhead that, that solves that problem. That's right.
懂了 所以它……
And yeah it makes sense that
这部分受力挺复杂的啊 这个穹顶会给火箭施加向四周的力
that's, that's a complex stress problem right there, is when that bulkhead goes to the side of the rocket.
有意思 您喜欢回到这里给大家展示这些东西吗?
Interesting. You like coming back and showing people this stuff?
当然~
Yeah.
我有一天看到一位女士 站在一级底部那里
I was here one day with a lady standing down there at the bottom of that first stage
她一边参观 一边记笔记 一边拍照
and she's looking at this thing and she's making notes and taking pictures.
所以我过去问她 "您对这东西感兴趣吗?"
And so I went down and they asked, I said You sure are mighty interested in this?
"您有什么想问的吗?" 她回答"是有几个问题"
"Do you have any questions?" "Well, I do have a few."
-我那天和她整整唠了四个小时  -我去
I spent 4 hours with that lady. Really?
她是一个学校的老师 呃……
She was a schoolteacher from a, uh,
她来自纽约州的北部
they were in upstate New York.
她说那边是靠近加拿大边境一个挺偏的地方
She said they were almost on the Canadian border in a very remote area,
你懂的 她的学生们平常根本没机会接触这些东西
and her kids didn't, you know, weren't exposed to any of this kind of stuff.
她当时又是拍照又是记笔记
She was taking pictures and taking notes.
跟我说 等回去要把这些东西给孩子们看
says I'm going to take all this stuff back and show my kids.
-哇 多好的老师啊  -是啊
I mean, teachers are amazing. Yeah.
真好
That's awesome.
登月任务有一个要求 就是不能把宇航员留在那 懂吧
So there was a mission rule, don't leave the astronaut on the moon. Okay.
所以登月舱上升级发动机 远处那台
So the ascent stage engine is over here.
如果你按了点火按钮 发动机没启动
And if you push the button and that engine didn't go,
它还有一个拉火绳
they actually had lanyards.
他们可以拽拉火绳 发动机就会启动
And they could pull this lanyard and that engine would burn,
发动机燃料是接触自燃的 阀门打开就能工作
because we're hypergolic so all you got to do is open the valves.
所以它上面有一个拉火绳
So they had to actually have a lanyard on that thing
宇航员只要一拉 发动机就启动了
and they could actually start that engine without anything except pulling this lanyard.
他们就是靠这样的发动机离开月球的?
This was the engine that got them off the moon?
是的
Yeah. Really? Yeah.
-所以他们相当于有一个备份方案  -是的
So. So they had a they had a backup plan. Yeah.
写着呢 登月舱上升段发动机
This lunar module ascent engine.
-真牛啊 -嗯
That's incredible. Yeah.
我一直感觉这挺妙的
I always thought that was really slick.
天空实验室实际上原本是土星五号的三级
Now the Skylab is actually the structure of the third stage.
它本身结构就是来自土星五号的三级
Okay. So the the structure of Skylab is actually the, the third stage.
如果你进到天空实验室的生活区内
And then if you go into the Skylab exhibit over here where you're standing,
那你实际位置是在原本装液氢的燃料罐里
you're actually inside what would have been the liquid hydrogen tank.
但它不需要去月球 所以这些燃料就都不需要了 对吧?
But it didn't go on to lunar orbit so you didn't need all this, right? Is that true?
它不需要去月球 所以前两级就能把它送进近地轨道
It didn't go to lunar orbit so the first two stages launched it into orbit.
天空实验室的发射没有用到三级火箭
We didn't have a third stage on the Skylab launch.
懂了 有意思
Got it. Interesting.
天空实验室自己 就是曾经的三级
The Skylab was the third stage.
-成为了美国第一个空间站  -是的
As America's first space station. Space station,
有意思
That's amazing.
您为天空实验室工作过吧?
Did you work during Skylab?
嗯 我们负责任务支持
Yeah, we had a mission support.
我们做了天空实验室的计算机系统 IBM负责的控制系统
Yeah, we did the computer system for Skylab and IBM worked with the control system.
这是捷联系统 使用控制矩陀螺仪和推进器作为备份
This was a strapdown system, used control moment gyros and thrusters as backup.
而IBM负责了控制系统上的大量工作
And IBM was responsible for a lot of the work done on the control system.
厉害
That's fantastic.
还有计算机 当时的计算机
And the computer, it was a computer of its day.
这个模型好棒啊 我喜欢
This model is pretty good. I like it.
我一开始在4200号楼工作
The thing we used to be in the 4200 building out there
然后我第一次到这 4708号楼的时候
and when I first came here working in 4708,
我就在吃午饭的时候 带着花生酱 果冻三明治 可乐 来这里研究这个东西
I'd come over here at lunch with my peanut butter and jelly sandwich and Coke and study this thing.
等下……所以这个东西已经……
So this was ... this was built before...
它从196?年……
This was, this was, and it was here in 19...
它一开始 在1965年是放总部大楼那边
It was in the headquarters building out there in 1965.
我当时经常午餐休息的时候过来研究这个东西
I used to come in and study this during my lunch break.
-真的?  -嗯
Really? Yeah.
所以当时您看着 自己将要造出来的东西 的模型
So this was what you were going to build and you guys were, you had a model of it.
-这也算是一种计算机辅助绘图了吧  -哈哈哈确实
So this was CAD? Oh, yeah. Computer aided drafting, right? That was it.
-建模 然后仿真  -当时才没这些呢
Modeling and simulation. We didn't have all this fancy stuff.
-模型为主  -对
Heavy on the model.  That's right.
-这张照片 哪位是您?  -左边
So, is this, which ones you? Left.
-这位吗?  -对
So this is you? Yeah.
您当时就像领导一样 短袖白衬衫黑领带
So you were like one of the official short sleeved shirt, black tie.
呃……
Well.
这是1967年的IBM 当时大家都这么穿
This is 1967, is at IBM, and that's the expected dress.
真的吗? 您怀念吗? 我感觉好惹眼啊
Really? Do you miss it? I mean, it looks pretty sharp, I think.
嗯 当然 我挺怀念的
Well, yeah, I think yeah, I really do.
我感觉现在的人都不怎么在乎这些 挺遗憾的
I think it's a shame that people just don't care anymore.
-您是指穿着吗?  -对 仪表挺重要的
About how they dress? Yeah. About how they look. That's important.
-因为您感觉注重自己仪表 才能展现出自己  -是这样
Because if you carry yourself with respect... That's right. It changes how you present. That's right.
而且还能改变其他人对你的看法
And it changes how other people might think about you too.
嗯 有意思
Oh, yeah. Oh, interesting.
跟大家讲讲这张照片吧 Luke
So tell me about this picture Luke.
在阿波罗12号 呃 13号吧 我们打算控制三级火箭撞月
On Apollo 12, well, Apollo 13, we were going to crash that third stage into the moon.
在阿波罗11号和12号的仪器舱上有S波段的转发器
Well, on Apollo 11 and 12, there's a S-band transponder on the instrument unit.
上面装有额外的电池 可以一直给它供电
We had an extra battery and we were going to power that thing
能一直追踪箭体到它撞月
so that we could track the instrument unit all the way until it impacted the moon.
但阿波罗11号上的设备 在船箭分离后大约一小时就坏了
Well, Apollo 11, that thing conked out about an hour after the crew separated.
遥测部分的人 做射频的
Well, the telemetry people, the RF guys,
他们认为原因来自系统中的同轴开关
they thought that it was because of a coaxial switch that we had in that system
于是进行了重新设计 到阿波罗12号上应该就没问题了
and we had a new design was going on Apollo 12 and everything would be good.
结果阿波罗12号还是发生了同样的故障
Apollo 12 came along, same thing happened.
我当时就在HOSC 负责其中一个控制台
Well, I was at the HOSC at the site, you know, out there on one of the consoles,
当船箭分离以后
and when the crew separated from the from the rocket,
你会发现一股强烈的阳光会直接照进仪器舱内部
you could see that there was bright sunlight shining down in the instrument unit.
正常仪器舱内是不会照进阳光的
Well, we weren't supposed to have bright sunlight in the instrument unit.
我们设计参数没这条
That's part of our spec, okay?
所以我的想法是 如果你看看……
So my theory was that if you look at
-故障点的话 你想看看故障点在哪吗?  -想!
where that happened, you want to look at where that happened? Yeah.
如果你观察这里
If you look right here,
-那个金色的盒子就是S波段转发器  -好的
that gold box there is the S-band transponder. Yeah. Okay?
它旁边挨着的就是发射机 下面就是小的同轴开关
Right next to it's the transmitter and the little coaxial switch down by that.
它伸出一根线 一路连接到上面这里的天线
And that went up to a set of cables that came around to antennas on the side of it up here.
-那里有一个小的全向天线  -看到了
There's a little small antenna there, it's a omni directional antenna. Yeah.
上面那个大的是定向天线
The bigger one up there is a directional antenna.
我当时想法就是 当船箭分离时
My theory was that when the crew separated,
我发现这个区域会受到阳光的强烈照射
I actually saw that there was very bright sunlight in this area right here.
所以我脑中想的 当时的情况应该是
So I came up, my theory was that what was happening is,
这条同轴线实际上 我们应该叫……呃……
this coaxial cable was actually what we call
同轴线有一个铝制的外导体层
well, this coax has an aluminum outer conductor.
中间一圈柔性的绝缘介质层 内部中心有一根铜线
And then you have this foam flex interior dielectric and you have a copper wire.
在太空 这种颜色的东西 比黑色要更热一点
Well, being this color stuff, in space, gets hotter than black.
-真的?  -黑体辐射那些东西 懂吧
Really? Okay. Blackbody radiation. All right.
所以我的想法是 这条同轴线被晒热
So my theory was that this cable was heating up
中间绝缘介质层熔化 导致内外层短路了
and melting that dielectric and caused that thing to short out.
那张照片里 我们手里拿的东西
Okay, so that picture over there, the stuff we're holding
是金色镀铝的聚亚酰胺薄膜 和登月舱下面包的一样
is the gold aluminumized kapton like on the bottom of the lunar module
而我旁边那人叫Nate 是负责热环境控制的
and Nate Kayola is the, he was the environmental control thermal guy.
当时想法就是用这样的薄膜
And so the idea was we would use this stuff
把同轴线槽和周边的设备都盖上
and cover the cable trays with it and then cover the equipment with it
因为我们发现其他一些周边设备也有丢信号的问题
because we also found several other measurements that we had lost
然后我们进行了一些测试
and we went in and did some tests.
我们取一些同轴线放入真空室
We took some of that cable, put it in a vacuum chamber,
附上加热垫 线缆也通上信号
put some heat tape on it, put signal through it,
加热垫可以模拟接近太空中的每平方英寸的发热功率
and the heat tape gave us so many watts per square inch that we expected in space.
结果大约一个半小时后 信号就断了
And sure enough, about an hour and a half into it, the signal quit.
我们给真空室恢复压力 把线缆固定好 拍X光片
We dumped cold air into the chamber to freeze that dielectric back, x-rayed the cables,
很明显 里外两层导体被短路了
and sure enough, that semiconductor was shorted out.
所以我们决定用聚亚酰胺膜包上
So that's why we decided to use this.
Nate 负责热控的 他想出的把同轴线槽和设备都包上的主意
So Nate was the thermal guy, and his idea was to wrap the cable trays and the equipment.
等到阿波罗13号 我们成功一路追踪三级火箭到达月球
When we got to 13, we tracked it all the way to the moon
并在之后的任务中工作良好
and all the rest of them worked fine after that.
所以您解决了这个问题?
So you fixed the problem?
呃……差不多是这样吧
So that was the, that was what that was all about.
-您和Nate? 太牛了  -嗯
You and Nate? Nate, yep. That's awesome.
当然了还有很多人的帮忙啦 毕竟还要用到真空室
And a handful of other people because, you know, you're dealing with the chamber
测试用的线还得找负责射频的同事们帮忙
and we had to get some cables made and the RF folks had to be involved.
-所以是一整个团队的功劳  -厉害
So it was a whole group of people working on it. That's awesome.
我们能不能到那边简单介绍下仪器舱呀?
What if we go right over here and we just do a brief of the instrumentation?
有点吵 因为它后面就是空调
So this is a little loud because of the air conditioning unit back there.
而这就是您负责的东西
But this is what you worked on.
对 仪器舱 位于三级顶部
Yes, this is the instrument unit, sits on top of the third stage.
基本上 它尽量把重量分布在这一圈上
Basically, the thing is set up like this so that you can distribute
your weight around the outside of the thing
并控制好整体的重心 你懂的
and control your center of gravity and so forth, you know.
当时想法是在阿波罗应用计划中
阿波罗应用计划 Apollo Application Program AAP
美国1966年启动的计划
用阿波罗计划的硬件继续开展载人航天科研任务
直接产物就是天空实验室
The hope was that we would go on with an Apollo Application Program
这样的布局与不同的导热板
and with this layout like this with the different thermal conducting panels,
可以调整设备位置 进行不同的实验
we could move equipment around and, you know, do different experiments.
它的顶端是遥测系统
So basically the top part of it is the telemetry system
从我手指的地方 有个桶一样的东西开始
"桶"就是飞控计算机
starting over here, where this looks like a barrel.
一直到下面球形的东西 这一段负责制导导航与控制 GNC
Coming on down to the sphere, that's kind of the guidance navigation control section.
从我站的地方到顶部空白的那块区域
From about where I'm standing on up to the blank panel,
负责电力与环境控制
this would be the power and the environmental control
黑色弯管连接的是脐带接口
and the umbilical plate attachment through that big black boot up there,
火箭的脐带就是在那里连接的
that's part of the, that's where the umbilical attaches.
-那个黑色的弯管吗  -对 大的那个
That boot right there? Yeah, the big one up there.
然后那三个大的长方体就是电池
Then these three large rectangular pieces were the batteries.
这侧的圆桶是集水器
The other thing that looks like a barrel was full of water.
作为环境控制系统的一部分
That's part of our environmental control system.
-整个这个圆环放在三级的顶部?  -对 三级顶部
So this thing sat on top of the third stage? Top of the third stage.
-控制整个火箭  -没错
And controlled the whole rocket. That's right.
顶上有一捆往下顺的线缆 看到没有
Those lines up at the top up there you see going down?
它们会一路下行连接火箭其他分级
Those were the lines that went down, connected to the other stages
从而获取它们的数据
to allow us to communicate with them.
厉害
That's awesome.
系统自己还要负责分离 断开线缆
And there were methods in the system for separation to disconnect the cable.
我之前还做过那边计算机的视频
And we made another video about the, the computer over there.
那是完全另一个东西了吧?
That's a whole different thing isn't it? Yeah.
如果观众朋友们想多多了解土星五号的计算机
av93701051
So I guess, I guess if you want to learn more about the computer for Saturn V,
可以过去看看那个视频
you should just go watch that video, I guess. But uh...
嗯 这些是存储 磁芯存储器 一个里有4000字的存储
Yeah, these were the memories. These were core memory, there's 4,000 words of memory in here.
那边墙上每块里面都有一个这样的东西
There's one of these in each one of these blocks on the wall over here.
这就是4000字的内容
That's 4,000 words.
放在今天可能只要针尖大小的芯片
4,000 words today probably fit on the head of a pin.
而它是磁芯存储 是不怕掉电的
But this is core memory, so it's non-volatile.
关机断电 再开机 它存的东西都还在
So if you shut your system down and bring it back up, it's still there.
天空实验室在天上飘了四年之后给它重启
When we powered up Skylab after being floating free in space for about four years,
发指令它马上就能重启
we powered it up, it came on instantly.
有磁芯存储器在 完全没出过错
With the core memory, we didn't have any errors of any kind.
厉害
That's awesome.
-挺棒的东西  -好用
So, pretty good stuff. It worked.
-还是纯手工打造的对吧?  -没错
It was made by hand too, right? And that's right.
女工们一点点手穿的 这些一层层核心
Ladies wove these things by hand. These core planes
用导线穿过这些小磁环
had little donuts with wires going through them.
这上面有8192个这样的小磁芯
There's 8,192 of those little magnetic cores on here.
一个模块上要14个这样的平面堆叠起来
There's 14 of those stacked up to make this module.
四个就能组成……这里的一个模块
And then there's four of those, one of these
就是这里的一个小模块
in each one of these.
所以这里就是4x4=16 16000字的存储 右边是另外16000字
So that's four, eight, 12, 16,000 words of memory and another 16,000.
在飞行时 两边会运行同样的飞行程序
When it's flying, the same flight program executing in both memories
对比计算结果 为了可靠性 要得到相同结果才行
and they're comparing the outputs and that's for reliability, make sure you get the same answer.
如果结果不同 就去分支里查找原因 然后继续飞
If you didn't get the same answer, you go into the subroutine and determine what happened and keep going.
因为没时间找休斯顿 你必须继续飞
You don't have time to call Houston. It has to, you have to keep going.
-实时的  -是的 实时的  -厉害
Real time. Real time. Yeah. That's amazing.
我印象中土星系列火箭所有飞行里
I think during all the Saturn flights,
加起来只有20 25次出错吧 并不多
I don't think there were probably more than 20 errors, 25 something like that. Not too much.
这些是逻辑……
These are the logic
逻辑部分吧 上面有晶体管
part of it. It had the transistors.
-不知道你见没见过  -哇您兜里还有一个  -嗯
I don't know if you've seen that before. Oh you have, you have one in your pocket? Yeah.
不知道你能不能拍清楚
I don't know if you can see this thing or not.
这些就是计算机里用的芯片
These are the chips that were used in the computer.
当时没有微处理器 没有集成电路
We didn't have microprocessors or integrated circuits.
约20mm²
这些闪亮的小正方形就是晶体管 大约1/32平方英寸大小
So each of these little shiny squares is one transistor, about a 32nd of an inch square.
真假? 上面那小点吗?
Really small down in there?
-最顶上这个小点  -好的
This little tiny thing up here at the top. Yeah. Okay. Okay.
这个芯片上有两个晶体管 这个上面有六个吧
So this one's got two transistors in it, and this one has about six.
最多应该能放九个
I think we can have at most nine.
整个计算机系统上有87000个晶体管
Total, we had 87,000 transistors in the computer system.
IBM在当今航天领域最新最常用的系统上 这样的空间能放180万个晶体管了
This little transistor here in the latest system that IBM has in the field, it's a very common system today,
in that space there's 18 million transisors.
现在的晶体管大小可能都……
So we're down to where transistors now
都能直接数出来用了几个原子了吧
are measured in numbers of atoms probably.
-太厉害了  -我觉得也是
That's amazing. I know. Yeah. Yeah.
您当时要是哪怕只有一个微处理器 会怎么样?
What would you have done back in the day if you'd had even one microprocessor?
呃
Well,
能换掉不少当时计算机吧
you'd replace most of that computer.
-真的?  -嗯
Really? Yeah.
但其实对于这东西来说
The thing about these, though, is
我能拿它设计一套系统 比如说要求它非常非常可靠
you can design a system like this and say, Well, I need this part to be very reliable.
这个要三冗余 那个不用特别可靠
I'll make it triple redundant. I need this to be not that reliable.
那我就双冗余 或者甚至只做一路之类的
Maybe I'll make it dual, maybe I'll just make this a single path type thing
这样的设计实现起来相对简单
A design like this is relatively easy to do that.
但对于微处理器来说
But in a microprocessor,
上面要是丢了任何数据 我可能就死了
if I lose anything on that processor, I'm dead meat.
-哇  -所以这些独立的小组件也是有很多优势的
Wow. So there's a lot of a lot of plus to having individual components.
真的? 靠堆硬件来解决问题
Really? Solve it with a hardware solution.
-看你要做什么事情吧  -嗯
Depending on your what you're trying to do. Yeah.
-任务有多重要  -各有优劣吧
How critical it is. Trade offs.
因为很多……在处理器上面这里很多线路是三冗余的
Because a lot of this, a lot these circuit was triple redundant in the, in the processor part.
而存储是双冗余的
Memory was dual redundant.
-然后两者对比  -没错
And it would compare. Yeah, Yeah.
Luke Talley 谜一样的男人 传奇一样的男人
All right. Luke Talley, the man, the myth, the legend.
感谢您的时间
Thank you for your time, sir. Yes, sir.
-能听您讲解这些真的倍感荣幸  -希望你喜欢
I'm absolutely honored to be your presence. Enjoyed it.
太感谢了 您去吃早点吧
Really appreciate it. I'll let you get on to breakfast.
所以您是怎么弄到那玩意的?  有人……您偷拿的吗?
So, how'd you get that? Somebody... you smuggle it out?
我自己做的
We, I made this.
-真假?  -真的
Did you really? Yeah.
-这玩意已经50多年了  -真假?
This thing is 50 years old. Really?
计算机那边有个人
One of the guys that was the, one of the computer,
有个人是负责……他是计算机零件的工程师
you know, the guy that was responsible for... the component-responsible engineer for the computer.
他有一堆这样的零件 送了我几个 我就做了个这样的东西
He had a bunch of parts, and he gave me these, and I made this little thing.
您让它们活到了今天是吧
You made it to last, didn't you?
对 我想想 应该是1968年做的
Yeah, I think I made this in 1968, probably.
-在登月之前?  -对  -厉害
Before we landed on the moon. Yeah, that's awesome. Yeah.
我一会给它拍个近景就走吧
I'll just get a tight shot of it, and we'll call it good.
左边是外壳 右边是两个小晶体管
So that's the housing on the left and two transistors on the right.
左边那个上面有晶体管吗?
Is there any transistors in that one on the left?
有啊 上面 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8  8个呢
Yeah, there's about... one, two, three, four, five six, seven or eight in there.
好的
Got it.
那个小正方形就是晶体管
The little squares will be the transistor.
晶体管要放在三个……这上应该看不到
The transistor stands up on three little... you can't see it from there.
发射极 基极 集电极?
Emitter, base, collector?
晶体管下面有三个焊球
There's three solder balls on the bottom of the transistor.
他们先是像印T恤那样画好导线的线路
So what they do is they form that conductor pattern, print it like you're printing a T-shirt,
放在烤炉中加热 然后拿出来
put it in the oven and fire it, and then bring it out.
晶体管的底下 有三个小焊球
And the transistors on the base of the transistors, they have three tiny solder balls.
把晶体管放在三条导电的线路上
So they take that and they stand it up on the where the three conductors come together,
让它放在三个焊球上就行 再放入烤炉
they stand it up on those three solder balls, put in another oven,
焊球熔化
and that melts the solder.
焊球熔化后的表面张力就能让晶体管完美对齐在线路上
And the melting solder, the surface tension of that melted solder
aligns that transistor perfectly with that conductor pattern.
他们试过很多种方法 这种是最好用的
They tried all manner of ways to do it, and that always, that was the best.
BGA
-就像球栅阵列一样吗?  -对 在今天这么叫
Is that called a ball grid array? Well, it is today.
-所以你们相当于在那时发明了这个?  -对
Well you all invented it then? Yeah.
-这算是史上首个生产样品吧  -真的?
This is probably one of the first examples of it. Really.
-哇 而我现在兜里有无数个这样的东西  -没错
Wow. And I've got millions of those things in my pocket now. Oh, yeah.
嗯  这是另一个
Yep. This is another one.
哇 您这好玩的东西真多呀 那是一片硅晶圆吗?
Man, you got all kinds of cool stuff in here. Is that silicon wafer?
对 那是硅晶圆 但下面这个角落看到了吗?
Now that, yeah, that's a piece of silicon up there but down here in this corner?
-嗯 -上面有 应该是8个还是10个小正方形吧
Uh huh. There are, I don't know, there's eight or ten of these tiny little squares on that.
上面每个都是这样的小晶体管
Each one of those is one of these transistors.
它来自IBM360计算机
That's out of an IBM 360 computer.
-更新的吗?  -呃 其实是同一时代的 都是60年代
A newer one. Well, this was this was the same vintage, 1960s.
-真的?  -嗯
Really? Yeah.
用在土星系列火箭仪器舱上的元件 曾经用在IBM360计算机上
So this same thing that we used on Apollo, it was used, I mean, on the Saturn instrument unit,
was being used on the IBM 360 computers.
它们差不多是同时代的东西
They came along about that same time.
-所以右边是用于飞行的硬件 而左边的不是  -没错
So this was flight hardware? Mm-hmm. This was not. Yep.
我手里这个 线路都是平铺在上面的
Wow. So these, these surface mount circuits sit flat
因为火箭上的振动非常强
because we have such a high vibration environment.
而左边这个用的是针脚 穿过电路板上的孔
But now here you see these are pin and hole circuits that go through holes in circuit boards.
芯片是站在电路板上的 它就不耐振动
And these stand up. you couldn't put that in a vibration environment.
两下可能就震掉了
It'd snap that thing in two in a heartbeat.
-而您在60年代做出了它们?  -是的
And you made this back in the '60s. Yeah.
一想到是您做的我就感觉好震撼
There's something amazing about the fact that you made that.
-您一直带着吗?  -嗯
You've been carrying it around ever since? Yeah.
时不时拿出来擦擦?
You polish it up every once in a while?
呃 有一阵没擦了吧 你能看出来
Uh, I haven't polished it in a long time. You can tell.
擦擦应该还能用
It could probably stand polishing.
这是您的备忘单吗?  什么东西?
Is this all your cheat sheets? What are these?
对 这是我这些年记的一些小纸条
Yeah, these are some old cheat sheets I put together over the years.
介绍这些系统吗?
So talking about the systems?
对 我最开始在这当志愿者的时候做的
Yeah, I made these up when I first started here volunteering 'bout,
在这干了应该能有12年了
I think I've been doing this 12 years, I think.
我把它们整理起来 用来……
Uh huh. And I put these together just as..
提醒我自己
remind me.
而大伙都可以来美国太空和火箭中心这里遇到您
And people can come visit you here. Yeah. US Space and Rocket Center.
您就在这里 慷慨分享您的知识
And you're just here and you're giving everybody all the knowledge.
嗯 一周几个小时吧
Yeah, here and there a few hours a week.
最爽的就是大家都能来美国太空和火箭中心这里
The cool thing about this is you can actually come to the US Space and Rocket Center.
如果你运气好 比如上辈子积德
If you're lucky, it's kind of like Groundhog Day.
运气好就能在这里遇到Luke
If you're lucky, you'll, you'll find Luke here.
嗯 这里像我这样穿白大褂的不少
Yeah, well, they're a bunch of guys with the white coats, like.
-各种讲解员  -对 差不多
All the docents. All that stuff. Yeah.
好啦 希望大家喜欢今天我与Luke Talley的行程与访谈
All right. I hope you enjoyed this interview with Luke Talley.
非常非常感谢Luke
Luke, thank you so much.
今天听到了好多关于土星五号的新知识
I have a newfound appreciation for all the things that went into the Saturn V.
太棒了 感激不尽
It's amazing. Thank you so much.
也感谢大家的观看
Also, thank you to you for watching
也感谢大家能赞助天天大聪明频道
and thank you for considering supporting over at SmarterEveryDay on Patreon.
如果您也想赞助 欢迎前往下方链接
If you'd like to do that, you can. It's at www.patreon.com/SmarterEveryDay.
可以解决我的经济情况 也能让我做出更多我想做的视频
That lets me like free myself from the financial worries and lets me make videos that I want to make,
也希望大家能喜欢我的视频
and I hope you enjoy them too.
不喜欢也没关系 来看我就很感激啦
So if not, no big deal. I'm just glad you're here. Glad you're watching and I'm grateful.
就这样 我是Destin
Anyway, that's it. I'm Destin.
祝大家天天大聪明~拜拜~
You're getting smarter every day. Have a good one. Bye.